大地驚雷
雖無人追趕  惡人亦倉皇逃跑
舊約: 箴言  第二十八章  第一節
背景音樂  依靠在上帝的臂膀下
"Leaning on the everlasting arms"
人們不會相信
People did not give it credence
一個小女孩能離開家鄉
that a young girl could leave home.
在冰天雪地的寒冬為父親報仇
And go off in the winter time to avenge her father's blood.
但事實就是如此
But it did happen.
那個懦夫湯姆·切尼射殺我父親的時候
I was just fourteen years of age
我只有十四歲
when a coward by the name of Tom Chaney shot my father down.
他不但殺了我父親  搶走他的馬
And robbed him of his life, and his horse.
還拿走了他褲袋堛漕漍竷[州金塊
And two California gold pieces that he carried in his trouser pant.
切尼是個雇工
Chaney was a hired man.
爸爸讓他到史密斯堡
And Papa had taken him up to Fort Smith
幫忙帶回他買下的小野馬駒
to help lead back a string of mustang ponies he'd bought.
在城  切尼被美酒吸引
In town, Chaney had followed to drink.
開始賭博  輸光了身上所有的錢
And cards, and lost all his money.
他認為他被騙了
He got it into his head he was being cheated.
回到住處取他的那把亨利步槍
And went back to the boarding house for his Henry Rifle.
當父親試圖阻止他時
When Papa tried to intervene.
切尼開槍殺了他
Chaney shot him.
切尼逃跑了
Chaney fled.
他本可以牽著馬慢慢走的
He could have walked his horse.
因為那座鎮上的人沒有一個去追趕他
For not a soul in that city could be bothered to give chase.
切尼自以為能逃過制裁
No doubt Chaney fancied himself, scott free.
但是他錯了
But he was wrong.
這個世界任何東西都是有代價的
You must pay for everything in this world,
欠下的終究都會被償還
one way or another.
除了上帝的恩澤
There is nothing free,
沒有什麼是免費的
except the grace of God.
是他嗎
Is that the man?
是我父親
That is my father.
如果你想親吻他
If you would like to kiss him,
請便吧
It would be all right.
他回家了
He's gone to home.
感謝上帝
Praise the Lord.
為什麼這麼貴
Why is it so much?
棺木的選材
The quality of the casket.
還有防腐的材料
And of the embalming.
死者保持這樣的外表是需要時間和工藝的
The life like appearance requires time and art.
化學藥劑十分昂貴  帳單埵雩埴蚖顳
And the chemicals come dear, the particulars are in your bill.
如果你想親吻他  請便
If you'd like to kiss him, It would be all right.
謝謝您  他的靈魂已經消散了
Thank you, the spirit has flow.
你電報上說只要五十美元
Your wire said fifty dollars.
你沒說清楚他是要被運輸的
You did not specify that he was to be shipped.
我們只有六十美元
Well sixty dollars is every cent we have.
我們都沒有錢住店了
That leaves nothing for our board.
亞內爾  你去看著遺體
Yarnell you can see to the body
運到火車站  然後護送回家
transport to the train station, and company it home.
我今晚會在這兒過夜
I'll have to sleep here tonight.
我還需要整理遺物和處理其他事宜
I still have to collect father's things and see some other business.
你母親從沒說過你要來辦什麼其他事宜
Your mama didn't say nothing about you settling no business here.
這是媽媽不知道的事
It's business mama dosen't know about.
好了  亞內爾  你可以走了
It's all right Yarnell, I dismiss you.
我可不這麼認為
I am not sure.
轉告我媽不要簽署任何文件
Tell mama not to sign anything
一切等我回家後將父親體面安葬好再說
until I return home and see that Papa is buried in his mason's apron.
你的出價可以接受  但我要在這過夜
Your terms are agreeable, if I might pass the night here.
在這兒  和這些死人一起嗎
Here, among these people?
"這些死人"嗎
These people?
待會兒還有三個心靈要在這埵w息
I'm expecting three more souls.
蘇堣  史密斯還有狗舌頭
Sullivan, Smith, and His-tongue-in-the-rain.
女士們先生們  聽好了
Ladies and gentlemen, beware
好好培養孩子  讓他們走上正路
and train up your children the way that they should go!
你們看看現在的我
You see what has become of me.
因為喝酒
Because of drink.
我殺了一個人
I killed a man.
就因為爭搶一把小折刀
In a triffiling quarrel over a pocket knife.
如果我年輕的時候能受到良好的教育
If I had received good instruction as a child...
請問哪位是警長
Could you point out the sheriff?
那個大鬍子
Him with the moustaches.
今天我本可以和我妻子兒女在一起
I would be with my wife and children today.
我不知道他們以後會怎麼樣
I do not know what is to become of them.
但是我希望妻子不會放手不管孩子們
But I hope and pray that she will not slight them
讓他們成為社會的敗類
and compel them to go into low company.
好吧
Well.
我殺了一個不該殺的人
I killed the wrong man,
這就是我在這的原因
is the which why I'm here.
如果我沒殺錯的話
Had I killed the man I meant to.
我肯定不會被判死刑的
I don't believed I'd a been convicted.
我看到人群中  有些人還不如我呢
I see men out there in that crowd, that's worse than me.
好了
Okay.
我被絞死之前  我想說的是
Before I hang, I would like to say.
沒有  我們沒抓到他
Naw, we ain't arrested him.
他們沒追上他  跑得太快了
Ain't caught up to him, but he lit out for the Territory.
我覺得他投靠幸運奈德·彼伯了
I would think that he throwed in with Lucky Ned Pepper,
他們昨天在波托河旁搶劫了一輛郵車
whose gang robbed a mail hack yesterday at the Poteau River.
那為什麼您沒有去搜捕他呢
Well, why are you not looking for him?
印第安區不在我的管轄範圍內
I ain't no authority in the Indian Nation.
湯姆·切尼現在歸美國法警管了
Tom Chaney is the business of the U.S. Marshal now.
那他們什麼時候去抓他呢
When will they arrest him?
近期是不太可能了  法警的人手不夠
Not soon, I'm afraid, the Marshals are not well staffed.
我實話跟你說吧
And I'll tell you, frankly,
切尼是通緝犯名單上的最後一個
Chaney is at the end of a long list of fugitives and malefactors.
我能雇個法警去追捕湯姆·切尼嗎
Could I hire a Marshal to pursue Tom Chaney?
你是不是經常僱傭一些賞金獵人啊
You have a lot of experience with bounty hunters, do you?
怎麼可能呢
That is a silly question.
我是來處理父親後事的
I am here to settle my father's affairs.
-就你一個人嗎  -隻有我能做
- All alone. - I am the person for it.
我媽的數學很差
Mama was never any good at sums.
而且她大字不識兩個
And she could hardly spell 'cat'.
我要看到殺害我父親的人被處以絞刑
I intend to see Papa's killer hanged.
好吧
Well, nothing prevents you
你的確可以僱傭法警
from offering a reward or from so informing the Marshals.
但報酬要豐厚  這樣才有人會去
It had to be real money though, to be persuasive.
切尼現在已經過河到了查克托區
Chaney's across the river, in Choctaw Nation.
查克托區: 印第安人半自治區
我會處理錢的問題  誰是最好的法警
I will see to the money. Who's the best Marshal?
我得想想
I'd have to weigh that.
威廉姆·沃特斯追捕能力過人
William Waters, is the best tracker.
他有一半卡曼其血統
He is half Comanche,
卡曼其族(北美印第安之一族)
看他追捕賞心悅目
and it is something to see him cut for the sign.
最暴脾氣的要屬大公雞考伯恩
The meanest, is Rooster Cogburn.
他鐵面無私  真正的硬漢
He is a pitiless man. Double tough.
他無所畏懼
Fear don't enter into his thinking.
但是他嗜酒如命
Hmm, he loves to pull a cork.
最好的人選應該是奎因
The best is probably, L.T. Quinn.
他總能活捉罪犯
He brings his prisoners in alive.
也許會因此偶爾失手
Now he may let one slip by now and again,
但是  他相信
but he believes that
就算是罪大惡極的人  也應秉公處理
even the worst of men, is entitled to a fair shake.
我在哪兒能找到這個大公雞
Where can I find this, Rooster?
廁所有人了
The jakes is occupied.
我知道考伯恩先生
I know it is occupied Mr. Cogburn.
我有事找您
As I said, I have business with you.
我的事情更緊急
I have prior business.
您已經在這堳搕F很久了  考伯恩先生
You've been at it for quite some time, Mr. Cogburn.
我的事情想做多久就多久
There is no clock for my business!
去死吧  你怎麼找到我的
The hell with you! How did you spot me here?
警長叫我去酒吧找找
The sheriff told me to look in the saloon.
酒吧的人說你在這兒  我們得談談
In the saloon they referred me here. We must talk.
酒吧根本就不接待女人
Women ain't allowed in the saloon.
我不算顧客  我才十四歲
I was not there as a customer. I am fourteen years old.
廁所有人了
The jakes is occupied.
有段時間不會出來
Will be for some time.
羅斯  運往耶爾縣  在車站存放
晚上好
Good evening.
如果你想睡在棺材  請便吧
If you would like to sleep in a coffin, It would be all right.
棉花你多少錢收
How much are you paying for cotton?
九分五收中低檔次的  十分收優質的
Nine and a half, for low and middlin' and ten for ordinary.
我門很早就把貨出手了
We got most of ours out early.
我賣給了小巖城的維茲紳兄弟
I sold to the Wizten brothers in Little Rock
價格是十一分
for eleven cents.
那你應該把剩下的也賣給他們啊
Then I suggest you take the balance of it to the Witzen brothers.
我們的確吧剩下的賣了
We take the balance to Witzen.
十分五的價格
We got ten and a half.
你為什麼要來告訴我這些呢
Why'd you come here to tell me this?
我們本來打算明年來這堸等芛N的
I thought we might shop around up here next year.
這麼看來  我們在小巖城那邊就好了
But I guess we are doing alright in Little Rock.
我是麥蒂·羅斯
I'm Mattie Ross.
弗蘭克·羅斯是我父親
Daughter of Frank Ross.
真是可憐啊
Aw, tragic thing.
我想說  你的父親令我印象深刻
May I say, your father impressed me.
他的人品很好
With his manly qualities.
他做商人分文必爭  卻還是個紳士
He was a close trader, but he acted a gentleman.
我的提議是將我父親買下的小馬駒
My propose was to sell those ponies back to you,
再賣還給你
that my father brought.
我想這恐怕是不行
Well that I fear, is out of the question.
我保證會給你送到的
I will see that they are shipped to you,
而且會盡快
at my earliest convenience.
我們現在不想要也不需要小馬駒了
We don't want the ponies now, we don't need them.
我想這與我無關吧
Well that hardly concerns me.
你父親買下它們  並且付錢了
Your father brought the ponies, and paid for them.
我們兩清了  我有收據的
And there is an end to it. I have the bill of sale.
那我要三百塊的補助
And I want 300 dollars
因為我父親的馬是在你的馬棚失竊的
for Papa's saddle horse that was stolen from your stable.
你應該找偷馬的人去討賬
You'll have to take that up with the man who stole the horse.
湯姆·切尼偷走了
Tom Chaney stole the horse
你應該負責保管好的馬
while it was in your care.
你要對此負責
You were responsible.
我很欽佩你的不懈努力
Yeah, I admire your sand.
但是你應該知道  我對此是不負責任的
But I believe you'll find I'm not liable for such claims.
你是保管人
You were the custodian.
如果你是開銀行的而銀行被搶劫了
If you were a bank and were robbed.
你不能就告訴儲戶們順其自然吧
You could not simply tell your depositors to go hang.
別跟我打比方
I do not entertain hypotheticals.
世道本來就已經很煩人了
The world as it is is vexing enough.
其次  你對馬的估價過高了
Secondly your evaluation of the horse is high.
你至少高估了兩百塊  你多大了
By about two hundred dollars. How old are you?
我跟你說  我的估價絕對是低價
If anything, my prices is low.
茱迪是一匹優質的賽馬種馬
My Judy was a fine racing mare.
我看到她
I've seen her
能馱著一個很重的騎手跳過八柵柵欄
jump a eight-rail fence with a heavy rider.
-我十四歲 -是嗎  真有意思
- I am fourteen. - Oh, well, it's all very interesting.
小馬駒是你們的了  你得收下
The ponies are yours, take them.
你父親的馬是被殺人犯偷走的
Your father horse was stolen by a murderous criminal.
鑒於我們之間的默示協議
I have provided reasonable protection
我已經為它做了足夠的保護措施
for the creature as per our implicit agreement.
我的馬廄管理員牙齒都被打掉了
My watchmen had his teeth knocked out,
他現在只能喝湯了
and can take only soup.
那我們法庭上見吧
That would take it to law.
你沒有理由起訴我
You have no case.
阿肯色州潔特律師也許不會同意
Lawyer J. Noble Daggett of Dardanelle, Arkansas may think otherwise.
陪審團估計也不會同意你的觀點
As might a jury.
一個寡婦和三個孩子的訴狀勝算不會小
Petitioned by a widow and three small children.
我會往你父親的賬戶
I will pay two hundred dollars
打兩百美元
to your fathers estate.
前提條件是  我要收到你律師的文件
When I have in my hand a letter from your lawyer,
免除我到今天為止的一切責任
absolving me of all liability from the beginning of the world to date.
茱迪的價格是兩百塊
I'll take two hundred dollars for Judy,
小馬駒是一百塊
plus one hundred for the ponies.
另有二十五塊
And twenty five dollars
是那匹湯姆·切尼留下的灰馬
for the grey horse that Tom Chaney left.
市場上很容易就能四十塊出手的
He was easily worth forty.
那一共是三百二十五塊
That is three hundred and twenty-five dollars total.
小馬駒不算在內  我是不會買的
The ponies have no part in it. I will not buy them.
那茱迪的價格就是三百二十五塊
Then the price for Judy is three hundred and twenty-five dollars.
就算是飛馬我也不會出這麼多錢的
I would not pay three hundred and twenty-five dollars for winged Pegasus.
還有  那匹灰馬根本就不是你的
As for the grey horse, it does not belong to you.
那匹馬是我父親借給湯姆·切尼的
The grey horse was lent to Tom Chaney by my father.
切尼只是借用而已
Chaney only had the use of him.
我會付給你二百二十五塊
I would pay two hundred and twenty five dollars.
但我要留著那匹灰馬
And keep the grey horse.
另外還有小馬駒我也收下
And I want the ponies.
我不接受
I cannot accept that.
我離開這堣妨幓N不會有和解了
There will be no settlement after I leave this office
-我們法庭上見  -好吧  我讓步
- and it will go to law. - All right, this is my last offer.
兩百五十塊
Two hundred and fifty dollars.
前提是我拿到先前說的免責文件
For that I get the release, previously discussed.
還有你父親的馬鞍
And I keep your father's saddle.
灰馬不由得你來賣
The grey horse is not yours to sell.
那馬鞍是無價的  我要留著它
The saddle is not for sale. I will keep it.
潔特律師會證明那匹灰馬的歸屬權
Lawyer Dagget will prove ownership of the grey horse.
他會發函向你追繳非法強佔財產的
He will come after you with a writ of replevin.
什麼  好吧  聽好了
What? All right, now look, listen very carefully.
我不會再讓步了
As I will not bargain further.
我要回小馬駒
I'll will take the ponies back,
那匹灰馬本來就是我的
and the grey horse, which is mine.
妥協價是...
And settle...
三百美元  就這麼說定了
For three hundred dollars. Now you must take that or leave it.
我豁出去了
And I do not much care which it is.
傑特律師是不會讓我
Lawyer Daggett would not wish me to
接受任何低於三百二十五塊的補償的
consider anything under three hundred and twenty-five dollars.
但是我想三百二十塊就夠了
But I will settle for three hundred and twenty.
如果那二十塊是提前支付的話
If I am given twenty in advance.
好了  現在我們再說說那個馬鞍
Now here's what I have to say about that saddle.
弗蘭克·羅斯的女兒嗎
Frank Ross's daughter.
哦  可憐的孩子
Oh, poor child.
你是準備在這兒呆一陣子
Are you are gonna staying with us,
還是你馬上就回家看你媽媽呢
or you hurrying back home to your Mama?
我想留在這兒  如果方便的話
I'll stay here, if you can have me.
我昨晚在收斂師那兒過的夜
I just spend last night at the undertakers.
陪著三具屍體
In the company of three corpses.
我覺得我像是以西結
I felt like Ezekiel.
以西結: 希伯來先知
舊約聖經以西結書之作者
在死亡谷中
In valley of the dry bones.
上帝保佑你
Then, God bless you.
你和祖母特納睡在一個房間
Now that you'll be rooming with, Grandma Turner.
我們得擠一擠了
We had to double up,
因為許多人都前來看絞刑
what with all the people in town come to see the hanging.
這些是你父親屋中的遺物
This was in your poor father's room.
這就是所有的東西了
That is everything.
這棟房子堥S有小偷的
There are no light fingers in this house.
如果你需要什麼來裝那把槍
If you need something for to tote the gun around?
我可以給你一個麵粉袋  只要五分錢
I can give you an empty flour sack for a nickel.
他在那兒發現了什麼
...about what he found up here,
我們離波特警官很近
and we're close enough to deputy Marshal Potter
所以我們就靠近那堨h調查了
that we thought we'd better ride over ourselves and investigate.
那麼你看到什麼了
And what did you see when you arrived?
一個女人  在院子那
A woman, was out in the yard.
她死了  臉上都是蒼蠅
Dead with blow flies on her face.
一個老人在院子堶
The old man was inside
他的胸脯被霰彈槍打開花了
with his breast opened by a scatter-gun
他的腳被燒焦了
and his feet burned.
他那時候還活著  但也只剩一口氣了
He was still alive, but just was.
他說是沃頓兄弟倆干的
Said it was them two Wharton boys had done it.
-他們聚在一起  喝醉了  -反對
- Rode up, drunk. - Objection.
道聽途說
Hearsay.
那可是臨終遺言  法官大人
Dying declaration, your honor.
反對無效  請繼續  考伯恩先生
Objection's overruled. Proceed Mr. Cogburn.
然後兄弟二人  奧多斯和賽思將他推倒在地
Them two Wharton boys, Odus and C.C. throwed down on him,
問他錢在哪兒  但是他沒說
and asked him where his money was, but he wouldn't tell them.
他們在他腳上抹上松子油  點火拷問他
They lit pine nut held them to his feet.
他說錢在一個水果罐頭中
He told them the money was in the fruit jar.
在煙熏屋旁的一塊灰色岩石下面
Under a grey rock at the corner of the smoke house.
然後呢
And then?
他死了  死時相當痛苦
Well he died on us, Passed away in considerable pain.
然後你做了什麼
What'd you do then?
我和波特警官找到煙熏屋
I made Marshal Potter and went out to the smoke house
發現那塊岩石被搬走了
and that rock had been moved,
然後那罐錢也不見了
the jar with the money in it was gone.
-反對  純屬猜測  -反對有效
-Objection, speculative. -Sustained.
你們在煙熏屋旁邊找到了那個灰岩石
You found a flat grey rock, in the corner of the smoke house.
下面有個洞
With a hollowed out space beneth it.
如果被告要陳述證據
If the prosecutor is going to give evidence,
我希望他能宣誓
I suggest he be sworn.
考伯恩先生  你在煙熏屋附近
Mr. Cogburn. What did you find,
找到了什麼東西
if anything, in the corner of that smokehouse?
有一塊平整的灰色岩石
We found a flat gray rock with
下面有個洞  堶惜偵繷ㄗS有
a hollowed-out space under it. Nothing there.
-然後呢  -沒有罐子  什麼也沒有
- Well then what did you...? - No jar or nothing.
那之後你做什麼了嗎
Well, what did you do then?
然後  我去到沃頓兄弟那
Well, rode up to the Wharton boys there,
離北福克河與加拿大河的匯流處不遠
near where the North Fork strikes the Canadian.
-..加拿大河支流  -你發現了什麼
- ...branch of the Canadian. - What did you find?
我用望遠鏡看到兄弟倆和他們的父親艾倫
I had my glass and we spotted the two boys and their old daddy Aaron.
他們和一些畜養豬在溪流岸邊
down on the creek bank with some hogs.
他們殺了一頭小豬
They'd killed a shoat.
然後便生火燒水
And a fire built up under a wash pot for scalding water.
之後你做了什麼
What did you do?
我對著艾倫喊  我們是美國法警
Announced we was U.S. Marshals, I hollered out to Aaron.
我要和他兒子們談談
I needed to talk to his two boys.
他掄起斧子
He raised an axe,
開始咒罵我們  並且侮辱法庭公正
and commence to cussing us and blackguarding this court.
那之後呢
What did he do then?
我後退幾步  躲開斧子
I backed away from the axe.
試著和他講點道理
Tried to talked some sense into him.
就在這個時候
While this was going on,
賽思躲在升起的蒸汽後面
C.C. edges over to the wash pot there, behind the steam.
拿起一把雙管獵槍
And picks up a shot gun.
波特看到了  但是一切都太遲了
Potter seen him, but it was too late.
賽思對著波特開火了
C.C. Wharton pulled out on Potter with one barrel.
然後想要打我  我就開槍了
Turned to do the same for me and I shot him.
他父親也掄起了斧子
And the old man raised the axe.
我開槍打了他
And I shot him.
奧多斯想要逃跑  我也對他開了一槍
Odus lit out, and I shot him.
賽思和他老爸倒地後就斷氣了
C.C. Wharton and Aaron Wharton were dead when they hit the ground,
而奧多斯只是被擊傷了
Odus was just winged.
那你發現裝著一百二十美元的罐子了嗎
Did you find the jar with a hundred and twenty dollars in it?
-反對  暗示性問題  -反對有效
- Leading. - Sustained.
之後發生了什麼
What happened then?
的確找到了堶惘酗@百二十塊錢的罐子
Found a jar with a hundred and twenty dollars in it.
奧多斯後來怎樣了
What became of Odus Wharton?
他在那兒坐著呢
There he sits.
您可以提問了  高迪先生
You may ask, Mr. Goudy.
謝謝  巴羅先生
Thank you Mr. Barlow.
考伯恩先生
Mr. Cogburn.
在你擔任美國法警職務的四年中
In your four years as a U.S. Marshal.
你對多少人開了槍
How many men have you shot?
我從不無緣無故開槍打人
Never shot nobody that didn't ask for it.
你並沒有回答我的問題
Well that was not the question.
多少個
How many?
開槍打的還是射殺的
Shot or killed?
咱們就限定在你射殺的吧
Let us restrict it to killed
這樣數目不至於大得說不清
So that we may have a manageable figure.
大概十二個
About twelve.
或者十五個  制止鬥毆  自衛反擊之類的
Fifteen. Stopping men in flight, defending myself, et cetera.
他說大概十二個
Around twelve he says.
或者十五個
Or fifteen.
那麼多  你甚至都沒法給出準確的數字
So many, you cannot keep a precise count.
我檢查了案件卷宗  可以提供準確的數目
I have examined the records, and can supply the accurate figure.
我估計算上沃頓家的那兩人  得有二十三個
I believe them two Wharton boys makes it twenty three.
就單單這一家
And how many members of this one family,
沃頓家  你殺了多少個人
the Wharton family, have you killed?
直系的  還是...
Immediate, or...
你是否還開槍打死了家中的兄弟達布·沃頓
Did you also shoot Dub Wharton, brother?
以及異母兄弟克里特·沃頓
And Clete Wharton, half-brother?
噢  克里特賣烈酒給切諾基人
Oh, Clete was selling ardent spirits to the Cherokee.
他拿著個大螺栓向我衝來
He come at me with a king bolt.
大螺栓
A king bolt?
你帶著槍  他朝你衝過去
You are armed, and he advanced upon you.
手奡N拿著個大螺栓
With nothing more than a King bolt?
還是從馬車牽引架上卸下來的
From a wagon tongue?
我見過有人被比螺栓還小的東西
I've seen men badly tore up with
撕成重傷  我是在正當防衛
nothing bigger than a king bolt. I defended myself.
回到我們的案子
Returning to the other encounter.
你碰上了艾倫還有他剩下的兩個兒子
With Aaron Wharton, and his two remaining sons.
你從藏身之處猛然躍起
You sprang from cover.
手堮陬菪直槍
With revolver in hand.
-就是那樣  -上好子彈準備射擊
-That'd be it. -Loaded and cocked.
要是沒上好子彈  我還怎麼開槍
Well if it ain't loaded and cocked, it don't shoot.
和他的兒子一樣
And like his son,
艾倫衝向了一個帶著武器的人
Aaron Wharton advanced against an armed man.
可他也有武器  他舉著把斧頭
Well he was armed, he had an axed raised.
我記得你曾作證說你後退躲開了艾倫
I believe you testified you backed away from Aaron Wharton.
-沒錯  -朝哪個方向後退
-That's right. -Which direction were you going?
我後退的時候都是向後的
I always go backwards, when I'm backing up.
很有趣
Very amusing.
他朝你衝去的方式和克里特差不多
Now, he advanced upon you much in the manner of Clete Wharton
拿著個可憐的螺栓
menacing you with that little
或者一卷報紙之類的玩意兒來威脅你
king bolt or rolledup newspaper or whatever it was.
對  他開始咒罵
Yes sir. He commenced to cussing
-嘴堜騊菗螂  -然後你向後退
-and laying about with threats. -And you were backing away.
槍戰發生之前你後退了多少步
How many steps before the shooting started?
七八步吧
Uh, seven, eight steps.
很好  而沃頓先生窮追不捨
Good, and Wharton keeping pace.
離他的營火越來越遠
Advancing away from his campfire.
七  八  步
Seven, eight, steps.
那有多遠
What would that be?
十五  或者二十英尺
Fifteen, twenty feet?
差不多吧
I suppose.
你能否向陪審團解釋一下  考伯恩先生
Will you explain to this jury, Mr. Cogburn.
為什麼沃頓先生被發現的時候
Why Mr. Wharton was found
倒在他的手盆邊上  一隻手還在火
immediately by his wash pot, one arm in the fire.
-袖子和手都燒著了  -呃
- His sleeve and hand smoldering. - Well...
你是否在射殺他之後還搬動了屍體
Did you move the body after you shot him?
我為什麼要那麼干
Why would I do that?
你否認把屍體拖到營火旁邊並把手扔進去
You did not drag the body over to the fire? Fling his arm in?
-我否認  先生  -兩個證人
-No, sir. -Two witnesses.
兩個目擊了事發現場的證人
Who arrived on the scene
能夠為屍體的位置作證
will testify to the location of the body.
你不記得搬動過屍體
You do not remember moving the body.
那麼  這就是一起當可憐的沃頓先生正在
So it was, a cold blooded bushwhack,
照料營火的時候發生的冷血襲擊
while poor Mr. Wharton was tending his campfire.
抗議
Objection.
要是屍體真在那兒  可能是我搬的
I, if that was where the body was I might have moved him.
我記不清了
I do not remember.
為什麼你要去搬動屍體  考伯恩先生
Why, would you move the body, Mr. Cogburn?
那些豬崽在附近跑來跑去  可能是它們挪的
Them hogs rooting around they might have moved him.
我記不清了
I do not remember.
傻逼娘娘腔
Pencil-neck son of a bitch.
-考伯恩先生  -幹嘛
-Mr. Cogburn. -What do you want?
我想跟您談一會兒
I'd like to talk to you a minute.
幹嘛
What is it?
他們告訴我您是真正有勇氣和毅力的人
They tell me you're a man with, true grit.
你想幹嘛  小女孩
What do you want, girl?
有話直說  該吃晚飯了
Speak up, it is suppertime.
我來卷吧
Let me do that.
你的煙絲太干了
Your makings are too dry.
我在找在蒙納克客棧門口
I am looking for the man who shot and killed my father,
槍殺了我父親弗蘭克·羅斯的男人
Frank Ross, in front of the Monarch boarding house.
他的名字叫湯姆·切尼
The man's name is Tom Chaney.
他們說他逃到了印第安人的地盤
They say he's over in Indian Territory,
我需要有人幫我追捕他
and I need somebody to go after him.
你叫什麼  小女孩
What's your name, girl.
我叫麥蒂·羅斯
My name is Mattie Ross.
我們家住在耶爾縣
We're located in Yell County.
我媽媽在家媟蚥U
My mother is at home looking after
我的妹妹維多利亞和弟弟小弗蘭克
my sister Victoria and my brother little Frank.
你最好回家去
You best go home to them.
他們需要人照顧
They'll need help with the charges.
切尼身上背著逃犯逮捕令
There is a fugitive warrant out for Chaney.
只要你能逮捕他  政府會獎勵你兩美元
The government will pay you two dollars
每追蹤一英里額外獎勵十美分
for bringing him in plus ten cents a mile for each of you.
在這基礎上  我會付給你五十美元的酬勞
On top of that, I will pay you a fifty dollar reward.
你到底是誰
What are you?
你那兜婺佽菑偵
What you got there in your poke?
天啊  一把柯爾特龍騎兵左輪
By God! A Colt Dragoon!
你個小不點
You're no bigger than a corn nubbin,
拿著這麼一把槍要幹嘛
what're you doing with a pistol like that?
我打算用它殺掉湯姆·切尼
Well I intend to kill Tom Chaney with it.
殺掉湯姆·切尼
Kill Tom Chaney?
要是法律沒能懲罰他的話
Well if the law fails to do so.
那這槍能幫上你的忙
Well that piece will do the job for you.
不過你最好找好支點
If you can find a high stump
身後頂著牆[形容這槍後坐力大]
to rest it on and a wall to put behind you.
這堥S有人認識我父親
Nobody here knew my father and I'm,
而且除非我親自動手
afraid nothing's is going to be done about Chaney
恐怕切尼會逍遙法外
except I do it.
我弟弟還是個孩子
My brother is a child,
我母親優柔寡斷  又悲痛致殘
and my mother is indecisive and hobbled by grief.
我不相信你有五十美元
I don't believe you have fifty dollars.
我跟斯通希爾上校簽了合約
I have a contract with Colonel Stonehill
他明天或者後天就會支付給我
which he will make payment on tomorrow or the next day
一旦律師簽好了手續
once a lawyer countersigns.
我不相信關於金錢的任何事情
I don't believe in fairy tales or sermons or stories about money,
小妹妹  不過謝謝你幫我卷的煙
baby sister. But thank you for the cigarette.
你媽媽還在等你回家吧  寶貝
Isn't your Mama expecting you home, dear?
我的事還沒處理完
My business is not yet finished.
弗洛依夫人  有新空出來房間嗎
Mrs. Floyd, have any rooms opened up?
特納奶奶那間  那床太擠了
Grandma Turner... the bed is quite narrow.
後面二樓倒是空出來了
The second-floor back did open up
但是  門廊上的那位先生
But uh, that gentleman on the porch,
剛住進去
has just taken it.
不過別擔心  寶貝
Oh but don't worry yourself, dear.
你沒有打擾到特納奶奶
You're not disturbing Grandma Turner.
我叫勒波義夫
My name is LeBoeuf.
我剛從耶爾縣過來
I just come from Yell County.
我們耶爾縣可沒有你這麼滑稽的牛仔
We have no rodeo clowns in Yell County.
你這些俏皮話對我是沒用的
A saucy line will not get you far with me.
我昨天早上見了你母親
I saw your mother yesterday morning.
她讓你馬上回家
She said for you to come right on home.
你到那兒去幹嘛
What was your business there?
我想你認識這個男人
This is a man I think you know.
你管他叫湯姆·切尼
You called him Tom Chaney.
至少我想是這樣  在我追蹤他的
I believe. All the months I've been
這幾個月間  他是瑟倫·切爾姆斯福特
tracking him he has used the name, Theron Chelmsford.
也是約翰·托德·安德森
John Todd Andersen,
還用過別的假名
and others.
他在路易斯安那州的門羅
He dallied in Monroe, Louisiana,
和阿肯色州的派恩布拉夫等地遊蕩
and Pine Bluff, Arkansas
然後他出現在你父親那兒
Before turning up at your fathers place.
那為什麼你沒在阿肯色州的派恩布拉夫
Then why did you not catch him at,
或者路易斯安那州的門羅抓住他
Pine Bluff, Arkansas or Monroe, Louisiana?
他特別狡詐
He is a crafty one.
我還以為他是那種粗人呢
I thought him slow-witted myself.
他只是看上去那樣而已
That was his act.
不錯的偽裝
It was a good one.
你是執法者嗎
Are you some kind of law?
沒錯
That's right
我是德州騎警
I'm a Texas Ranger.
在那個州  你大概還算是個人物
That may make you a big noise in that state
在阿肯色州你該知道德州式的
in Arkansas you should mind that your Texas trappings and title
馬具和頭銜可沒什麼吸引力
do not make you an object of fun.
你為什麼一直徒勞地在追捕切尼
Why have you been ineffectually pursuing Chaney?
他在德州韋科槍殺了州參議員比波斯
He shot and killed a state senator named Bibbs in Waco, Texas.
比波斯家發出了懸賞
Bibbs family have put out a reward.
切尼為什麼會槍殺州參議員
How came Chaney to shoot a state senator?
我聽說與一條狗的糾紛有關
My understanding is there was an argument about a dog.
你知道切尼現在何處嗎
You know anything about the whereabouts of Chaney?
他在印第安人的地盤
He is in the Territory, and I
而且我對你拿到賞金不抱多大希望
hold out little hope for you earning your bounty.
-怎麼說  -我的人會先你一步拿到賞金
-Why is that? -My man will beat you to it.
我雇了一位最厲害的執行法警
I have hired a deputy marshal, the toughest one they have
而且他對據說和切尼聯繫密切的
and he is familiar with the Lucky Ned Pepper gang
奈德·彼伯幫很熟悉
that they say Chaney has tied up with.
那我就加入你和你的法警吧
Well, I will throw in with you and your Marshal.
不  考伯恩警官和我兩個人就夠了
No, Marshal Cogburn and I are fine.
我們合作會更有優勢
It'll be to our mutual advantage.
我想你那位警官會對那地方很熟悉
Your Marshal, I presume, knows the Territory.
而我熟悉切尼  活捉他至少得兩個人
I know Chaney. It is at least a two-man job taking him alive.
抓到切尼之後他得被押回史密斯堡受絞刑
When Chaney is taken he is coming back to Fort Smith to hang.
我不能讓他因為
I am not having him go
槍殺了什麼州議員而被押回德州受絞刑
to Texas to hang for shooting some senator.
他在哪兒受絞刑並不重要  對不對
It is not important where he hangs, it is?
對我來說重要
It is to me.
對你來說呢
Is it to you?
對我來說這意味著一大筆錢
It means a great deal of money to me.
我跟了他好幾個月
It's been many months' Work.
我很遺憾你的工資並不是按月支付
I'm sorry that you are paid piecework not on wages
還被這白癡耍得浪費了一整個冬天
and that you have been eluded the winter long by a halfwit.
你說的話可真是冷酷無情
You give out very little sugar with your pronouncements.
我坐在那兒看著你的時候
While I sat there watching
我還在考慮要不要奪取你的初吻
you I gave some thought to stealing a kiss
儘管你還小  又病泱泱的
though you are very young and sick and
而且  對我也沒什麼吸引力
unattractive to boot, but
可現在  我倒是想要
now I have a mind to give
用皮帶好好抽你個五六下
you five or six good licks with my belt.
兩樣都不合我口味
One would be as unpleasant as the other.
我倒是給你個建議吧  把梳子沾濕
If you wet your comb,
說不定能把那頭亂毛梳平
it might tame that cowlick.
麥蒂  我希望你能把這些事務
Mattie, I wish you would leave these matters
完全移交給我處理  或者至少得
entirely to me or at the very least
在簽那些條約之前
give me the courtesy of
賞臉咨詢在下的意見
consulting me before entering such agreements.
我不是在責怪你  可我不得不說你這種
I am not scolding you, but I am saying your head strong ways,
固執的作風總有一天將使你走進死胡同
will lead you into a tight corner one day.
我相信隨信附上的文件
I trust the enclosed document
能讓你處理完事務  回到耶爾縣來
will let you conclude your business and return to Yell County.
您的  J·諾貝爾·達吉特
Yours, J. Noble Dagget.
你今天看起來就跟我昨天一樣糟
I was as bad yesterday as you look today.
我被逼地跟特納奶奶同床共枕
I was forced to share a bed with Grandma Turner.
我和特納奶奶不熟
I'm not acquainted with Grandma Turner.
既然她住在這個城市
If she is a resident of this city
要是她染上了什麼疾病  我可不奇怪
it does not surprise me that she carries disease.
這個瘧疾肆虐的地方毀掉了我的身體
This malarial place has ruined my health.
也毀掉了我的生意
As it has my finances.
我欠你錢
I owe you money.
你可別認為我佔了你便宜
You have not traded poorly.
噢  可不嘛
Oh, certainly not.
我為了一匹不屬於我的馬
I'm paying you for a horse
付給你一筆錢
I do not possess.
然後我還從你手上買回了一群沒用的小馬駒
And have bought back a string of useless ponies
我還賣不出去
Which I cannot sell again.
你忘了那匹灰馬
You're forgetting the Grey horse.
-劣馬  -你看問題的角度有失偏頗
-Crowbait. -You are looking at the thing in the wrong light.
我看問題的角度來自上帝永恆的真理
I am looking at it in the light of God's eternal truth.
你的病讓你過於悲觀了
Your illness is putting you down in the dumps.
你很快就會找到買家買那些小馬了
You will soon find another buyer for the ponies.
我倒是有個暫定的訂單  十美元一匹
Well I have a tentative offer of ten dollars per head.
來自小石城的菲茨肥皂廠
From the Pfitzer Soap Works of Little Rock.
就這麼毀掉那些生氣勃勃的小馬太可惜了
It would be a shame to destroy such spirited horseflesh.
可惜就可惜吧  這生意本來就談不成
So it would. I'm confident the deal will fall through.
我要匹小馬
Look here, I need a pony
我會給你十美元來買一匹
and I will pay ten dollars for one of them.
不  那是批發價  不  不
No. That was lot price. No no.
等等
Wait a minute.
我們又做上生意了嗎
Are we trading again?
這匹馬真美
This one is beautiful.
他意識不到他身上有個騎手
He don't know he got a rider.
您太輕了
You're to light.
他以為身上有只虱子
He think he got a horsefly on him.
他精力非常旺盛
He's very spirited.
我就叫他"小黑"吧
I'll call him 'Little Blackie'.
好名字
Das a good name.
他愛吃什麼
What does he like for a treat?
小姐  他是匹馬
Well ma'am, he's a horse.
所以他愛吃蘋果
So he likes apples.
替我謝謝斯通希爾先生
Thank Mr. Stonehill for me.
不  小姐  我沒資格提您的名字
No ma'am, I ain't supposed to utter your name.
看  睡著了
See. Sleep.
沒關係  我會叫醒他的
That is fine, I will wake him.
考伯恩警官
Marshal Cogburn.
是我  麥蒂·羅斯  你的僱主
It is I, Mattie Ross, your employer.
你還有多久能出發
How long til you are ready to go?
去哪兒
Go where?
去印第安區抓湯姆·切尼
Into the Indian Territory. In pursuit of Tom Chaney.
噢  你就是那個坐擁金山的可憐小女孩
Oh, You're the bereaved girl with stories of El Dorado.
哈  你有多少錢
Huh, how much money you got there?
我說抓到切尼就給你五十美元
I said fifty dollars to retrieve Chaney.
你不相信我
You did not believe me?
我不知道
Well, I did not know.
你讓人捉摸不透
You are a hard one to figure.
你準備好出發要多長時間
How long for you to make ready to depart?
悠著點兒  小妹妹
Well uh, hold on sis.
我記得你的任務  我可不記得答應過
I remember your offer but do not remember agreeing to it.
要是我得去和奈德·彼伯幫幹架
If I'm to go up against, Ned Pepper.
我得要一百美元
Then I'll need a hundred dollars.
就是這個價  一百美元
That much I can tell you. A hundred dollars.
逮回你的人  一百美元
To retrieve your man, a hundred dollars.
得先付五十美元
I will take that fifty dollars in advance.
當作路費花銷
There will be expenses.
你這是在試圖愚弄我
You are trying to take advantage of me.
我給你的是兒童折扣價
I am giving you the children's rate.
我可不是騙子  我只是個住在
I am not a sharper, I am an old man
中國人開的雜貨鋪後頭睡在繩床上的老頭
sleeping in a rope bed in a room behind a Chinese grocery.
我一無所有
I have nothing
你就想在威士忌媥K死吧
You want to be kept in whiskey.
我可用不著買那個
I don't have to buy that,
我沒收就行
I confiscate it.
我可是法庭警官
I am an officer of the court.
謝謝
Ah, thank you.
一百美元  就這個價
Hundred dollars, that's the rate.
那我就不討價還價了
I shall not niggle.
我們今天下午能出發嗎
Can we depart this afternoon?
我們
We?
你不能去  這不包括在任務
You're not going, that is no part of it.
你要是以為我會傻到給你五十美元然後
You have misjudge me if you think I am silly
眼巴巴看著你揚長而去  你就大錯特錯了
enough to give you fifty dollars and simply watch you ride off.
我是個合法的美國法警
I am a bonded U.S. Marshal.
那種話對我可沒用
That weighs but little with me.
我得看著你把這事做完
I will see the thing done.
該死  我可不能一邊扮硬漢
Damn ducks. I can't go after Ned Pepper
追捕奈德·彼伯  一邊又照顧個小孩
and a band of hard men and look after a baby at the same time.
我可不是小孩
I am not a baby.
我可不會在那種房間埵陰i暖床
I will not be stopping at boarding
桌子上擺著熱飯熱菜的客棧媟硫}
houses where there is warm beds and hot grub on the table.
我會風馳電掣  風餐露宿
I'll be traveling fast and eating light.
最多在地上打個小盹兒
What little sleeping is done will take place on the ground.
我以前也露過一次營
Well I have slept out a night before.
爸爸去年夏天帶我和小弗蘭克
Papa took me and Little Frank
去佩蒂吉恩州立公園獵過一次浣熊
coon hunting last summer on the Petit Jean.
我們在森林堳搕F整整一晚上
We were in the woods all night.
我們升起了一大簇篝火  還講鬼故事
We sat around a big fire and Yarnell told ghost stories.
我們玩的很開心
We had a good time.
獵浣熊
Coon hunting!?
咱這可不是什麼獵浣熊
This ain't no coon hunt!
這主意和獵浣熊差不多
It is the same idea as a coon hunt.
這跟獵浣熊可差了十萬八千里
It don't come within forty miles of being a coon hunt!
你不過是好大喜功而已
You are just trying to make your work sound harder than it is.
給你錢
Here is the money.
我的目標是抓住湯姆·切尼
Now I aim to get Tom Chaney,
要是你沒膽  我就找個有膽子的人
and if you are not game, I will find somebody who is game.
到目前為止我發現你只會說空話
All I have heard out of you so far is talk.
我知道你能喝威士忌  還能打呼嚕吐痰
I know you can drink whiskey and snore
躺在污穢的床上  抱怨自己悲慘的際遇
and spit and wallow in filth and bemoan your station.
然後就是自吹自擂
The rest has been braggadocio.
他們說你有勇氣  所以我才來找你
They told me you had grit and that is why I came to you.
我花錢可不是雇你來說空話的
I am not paying for talk. I can get all
我在那客棧奡N聽夠了
the talk I need and more at the Monarch Boarding House.
把你的錢留下
Leave your money.
明早七點來這兒找我
Meet me here tomorrow morning
然後我們出發去"獵浣熊"
at seven o'clock and we will begin our coon hunt.
最摯愛的母親
Dearest mother,
我即將開始一段偉大的冒險
I'm about to embark on a great adventure.
我聽說湯姆·切尼逃入了荒野之中
I have learned that Tom Chaney has fled into the wild.
而我將協助當局將他捉拿歸案
And I shall assist the authorities in pursuit.
你知道爸爸總讓我堅信正義
You know that Papa would want me to be firm in the right.
就像他一直做的那樣
As he always was.
所以別為我擔心
So do not fear on my account.
縱使走過死亡籠罩的幽谷
Though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death.
我也不怕遭害[聖經詩篇廿三篇四節]
I shall fear no evil.
萬物的造物主俯視著我  而且
The author of all things watches over me, and
我有匹好馬
I have a fine horse.
親親小弗蘭基  捏捏維奧萊特的臉
Kiss Little Frankie for me and pinch Violet's cheek.
我父親的死  終將迎來復仇
My Papa's death will soon be avenged.
我要出發去查克托區了
I'm off for the Choctaw Nation,
考伯恩警官呢
Where's Marshal Cogburn?
走了
Went away.
留了這個給你
Left this.
這有張回家的車票
Here inside is a train ticket for your return home.
用它回家去
Use it.
當你看到這封信時
By the time you read this,
我已經穿過河到印第安區了
I will be across the river in the Indian Nation.
你不可能追上來的
Pursuit will be futile.
我會帶切尼回來的
I will return with your man, Chaney.
讓我自己來完成
Leave me to my work.
魯本·考伯恩
Reuben Cogburn.
那是考伯恩法警嗎
Is that Marshal Cogburn?
對
That is the man.
他旁邊是誰
Who's he with?
不知道
I do not know.
帶我過去
Well, take me across.
那你就是那個逃犯
So, you're the runaway.
他告訴我  你一旦出現
Marshal told me you'd show up.
就帶去見警長
I'd present you to the Sheriff.
那是瞎編的  放開我的馬
That is a story. Let go my horse.
我過河有急事
I have business across the river.
如果你還是不帶我過去
If you don't turn around and take me across,
那我們就法庭上見
You may find yourself in court where you don』t want to be.
我有個好律師
I have a good lawyer.
小黑  衝過去
Go, Little Blackie.
加油
Come on.
真是匹好馬
That is quite a horse.
我用十美元買下它
I'll give you ten dollars for him.
用你從我這偷來的錢嗎
From the money you stole from me?
那不是偷  我不已經去抓你要的人了嗎
That was not stolen, I'm out for your man.
我們協商好一起走的
I was to accompany you.
如果我不去  協議便不生效
If I do not, there is no agreement
那你就是偷我的錢
and my money was stolen.
快把這孩子送回擺渡那去吧
Marshal, put this child back on the ferry.
山高路遠  這簡直就是浪費時間
It's a long road, and time is a-wasting.
若我現在回去
If I go back, it's to the U.S. Marshal's office
我會去警署報告  你偷了我的錢
to report the theft of my money.
考伯恩法警  "追上來也沒意義"
And futile, Marshal Cogburn, "Pursuit would be futile"?
的沒意義你都拼錯了
It's not spelt F-U-D-E-L.
我真要打你屁股了
It's time for your spanking.
你再老三老四
Now you do as the grown-ups say!
我就拿鞭子抽爛你的腿
Or I will get myself a birch switch and stripe your leg!
法警  你就眼睜睜地看著他這麼打我嗎
Are you going to let him do this, Marshal.
不會  勒波義夫  放下鞭
No, I don't believe I will. Put your switch away, LeBoeuf.
不行  我開始了就不能停下
I aim to finish what I started.
那估計會是你人生中犯下的最大的錯誤
That'll be the biggest mistake you ever made,
你這個德州傻牛仔
you Texas brush-popper.
竟然被一小姑娘擺佈
Hoorawed by a little girl.
我真不習慣生這麼大的火堆
I am not accustomed to so large a fire.
在德州  我們用小樹枝生小火
In Texas, we will make do with a fire of little more than twigs
或是用水牛的糞便
or buffalo chips.
用豆子來維持過夜火
Heat the nights rations of beans.
騎警隊規定
And, it is Ranger
不能在生火的地方搭帳篷
policy never to make your camp in the same place as your cookfire.
在野外暴露自己的行蹤  是不明智的
Very imprudent to make your presence known in unsettled country.
你怎麼知道巴格比那有情報
How do you know Bagby will have intelligence?
他開了家店
He has a store.
這樣就有消息來源了嗎
That makes him an authority on movements in the Territory?
現在我們身在荒野
We have entered a wild place.
不管是誰
Anyone coming in,
都需要食物的補給
wanting any kind of supply,
所以那是必經之路
cannot pick and choose his portal.
你這樣做有必要嗎
That is a piece of foolishness.
這季節蛇都冬眠了
All the snakes are asleep this time of year.
我有聽說過冬眠起來的蛇
They've been known to wake up.
我也要根繩子
Well, let me have a rope, too.
你就不用了
A snake would not bother you.
又小又瘦的  蛇才不會喜歡
You are to little and boney.
去打點明早用的水  放在火堆旁
You should fetch the water for the morning and put it by the fire.
-小溪要結冰了  -我才不去
- The creek'll ice over tonight. - I'm not going down there again.
你想要的話  就自己去打
You want anymore water, you can go fetch it yourself.
你該慶幸  這地方這麼容易打到水
You're lucky to be traveling in a place with a spring so handy.
在我那兒  連續幾天都看不到一滴水
In my country you can ride for days and see no ground water.
我只能從馬蹄印塈迉X點髒水喝
I have lapped filthily water from a hoofprint.
這已經算幸運了
and was glad to have it.
若我遇到一個德州牛仔
If I ever meet one of you Texas waddies
說他從未喝過馬蹄印堛漱
who says he had never drank water out of a horse track
那我會跟他握手
I think I'll shake his hand
請他抽丹尼爾·韋伯斯特雪茄
and give him a Daniel Webster cigar.
你不相信
You do not believe it?
前二十五遍還相信
Oh, I believed it the first twenty-five times I heard it.
說不定  還真有可能是真的
Maybe, maybe this is true.
說不定舔髒水是騎警隊的規定
Maybe lapping water off the ground is Ranger policy.
你太無知了  考伯恩
You're getting ready to show your ignorance now, Cogburn.
我不介意你拿我開玩笑
I don't mind a little personal chaffing.
但我不想聽到
But I won't hear anything
任何拿騎警隊做嘲諷對象的屁話
against the Ranger troop from a man like you.
你們騎綿羊都出名了
How long have you boys been mounted on sheep down there?
就算你的馬全部倒下了
My white Appaloosa will still be galloping
我的白馬依然能馳騁
when that big American stud of yours is winded and collapsed.
再敢開玩笑的話
Now make another joke about it.
你是想用你那三寸不爛之舌
You are only trying to put on a show for this girl Mattie
在小姑娘面前做表演吧
with what you must think is a keen tongue.
你說話怎麼跟女人似的
This is like women talking.
是啊  沒錯
Yes, that is the way!
你弄得我在小姑娘眼  顯得特蠢
Make me out foolish in this girl's eyes.
我想她已經知道你是什麼貨色了
I think she has got you pretty well figured.
想聽"午夜訪客"嗎
Would you two like to hear the story of "the Midnight Caller"?
其中一個扮訪客
One of you is gonna have to be the caller.
我教你說什麼
Now I'll tell you what to say.
我扮演其他角色
Now I'll do all the other parts myself.
-早  警官  -早
- Good morning, Marshal. - Morning.
勒波義夫先生呢
Where's Mr.  LeBoeuf?
去溪邊解手去了
Down by the creek performing his necessaries.
考伯恩警長  我們正好需要私自協商下
Marshal Cogburn, I welcome the chance for a private parley.
你和勒波義夫先生之間  應該有
I gather that you and Mr. LeBoeuf have come to some,
某種協議吧
some sort of agreement.
作為你的僱主
And as your employer I believe
我有權知道  詳細內容
I have the right to know the particulars.
詳細內容
The particulars...
我們會把切尼交給德州執法官
...is that we bring Chaney down to the magistrate in San Saba Texas
那有豐厚的懸賞等我們去拿
where they have a considerable reward on offer, which we split.
我不想讓他被帶到德州
I did not want him brought to Texas,
不想讓他在德州服法
to have a Texas punishment administered for a Texas crime.
這不是我們的協議
That was not our agreement.
你不是希望他被抓  然後服法嗎
What you want is to have him caught and punished.
我要他為我爸服法
I want him to know he's being punished for killing my father.
那麼  你可以親口告訴他
Well, you can let him know that. You can tell him to his face.
還可以吐他口水
You can spit on him.
或者叫他吃沙  我會幫你把人按著
and make him eat sand out of the road. I can hold him down.
如果你想的話
If you want,
我會把他打得皮開肉綻
I'll flay the flesh off the soles of his feet,
然後幫你找印第安辣椒抹上去
and find you Indian pepper you can rub into the wound.
這樣不值一百美金嗎
Isn't that a hundred dollar value?
不值
No, it is not.
既然我付了錢  你就應該服從我
When I have brought and paid for something, I will have my way.
若不服從  為什麼我要付你錢
Why do you think I'm paying you, if not to have my way.
你現在要明白
It is time for you to learn.
不是所有細節都能按照你的意願走
You cannot have your way in every little particular.
若你不滿意
If you find I fail to satisfy your terms,
等追捕結束後  我退你錢
I'll return your money at the end of this expedition.
等我和小黑回去後
Little Blackie and I are ridding back to
要把這些告訴警署  這是欺詐
the U.S. Marshal's office. This is fraud.
該死的
God damn it!
怎麼了
What's going on?
我們在談生意
This is a business conversation.
談生意
Is that what you call it?
看起來  你還是被小姑娘擺佈
Sounds to me you're still being hoorawed by a little girl.
-你說  擺佈  -沒錯
- You say, hoorawed? - That was the word.
沒有擺佈  我和警官的協議
There is no hoorawing in it. In my agreement with the Marshal,
比你的早  這有法律效應的
antedates your. It has the force of law.
法律效應
The force of law?
他可是個惡名昭彰的混球
This man is a notorious thumper.
他跟著昆特媞落麭B搶劫
He rode by the light of the moon with Quantrill,
還有血腥比爾·安德森
and Bloody Bill Anderson.
他們是守法公民  德州佬
Them men was patriots, Texas trash.
在堪薩斯州的勞倫斯  欺殺婦孺
They murdered women and children in Lawrence, Kansas.
簡直一派胡言
That's a God damn lie!
你在哪兒服役
What army was you in, Mister?
什堣猁i特市
I was at Shreveport.
先是跟著柯比·史密斯  然後
First with Kirby Smith, then with...
從屬哪個部隊
What side was you on?
北佛吉尼亞部隊  考伯恩
I was in the army of Northern Virginia, Cogburn.
我說這個也不會掉腦袋
And I don't have to hang my head when I say it.
若你跟的是昆特媞葉漯
If you had served with Captain Quantrill.
首長  昆特媞葉漯
Captain! Captain Quantrill.
確實是他
That...indeed.
-不說了  勒波義夫  -哪個首長
- You had best let this go, LeBoeuf. - Captain of what?
很好
Good, then!
德州那邊可沒這個閒錢給我
There're not sufficient dollars in the state of Texas,
聽你扯屁話
to make it worth my while to listen to your opinions.
我們之間的協議作廢了
Our agreement is nullified.
正合我意
That suits me.
分道揚鑣  自力更生吧
It's man for himself.
恭喜你  考伯恩
Congratulations, Cogburn.
成功從一個搶劫犯晉陞為保姆了
You've graduated from marauder to wetnurse.
再見
A-dios.
我們不需要他  是吧  警官
We don't need him, do we Marshal?
會需要他的夏普斯卡賓槍吧
We'll miss his Sharps carbine.
這堨i不是什麼太平之地
It's apt to get lively out here.
住手
Hey!
快跑
Go on.
待在這兒  小妹妹
Stay here, sister.
我去見巴格比
And I will see Bagby.
切尼來過嗎
Has Chaney been here?
沒有
No.
寇可·海斯兩天前來過
Coke Hayes was, two days ago.
寇可和狗屎運奈德一夥的
Coke runs with Lucky Ned.
他用這個買了東西
He bought supplies, with this.
是爸爸的金幣
Well, this is Papa's gold piece.
湯姆·切尼  等著  我們來了
Tom Chaney here we come.
這金幣到處都是
It is not the world's only California gold piece.
可在這少見
They are rare here.
是很少見
They are rare.
就算是切尼的
But if it is, Chaney's,
他加入狗屎運奈德並不是唯一的可能性
Just as easily mean that Lucky Ned
他也有可能是被狗屎運奈德殺人劫財了
and his gang fell upon him, as that he fell in with them.
切尼現在可能已經是屍體了
Chaney could be a corpse.
這會令人很失望的  警官
That would be a bitter disappointment, Marshal.
那我們現在該怎麼辦
what would we do?
繼續追捕
Um, pursue them.
不管怎麼樣  奈德和法警的賬還沒算清呢
Ned's unfinished business for the marshals anyhow.
抓到他  就等於就抓到切尼了
Or when we have him we will also have Chaney.
起碼知道切尼屍體所在
or we can learn the whereabouts of his body.
巴格比不知道他們往哪兒走了
Bagby didn't know which way they went.
但起碼  他們從這經過過
But now we know they come through here.
這兒只有一兩條路好走
They couldn't be going but one or two ways.
一條是朝著旋梯山朝北走
Heading north, towards the Winding Stair Mountains.
另外一條就是朝西走
Pushing further west.
我猜是北邊  那容易搶到東西
I suspect north. There is more to rob.
我買了家餐館
I bought an eating place.
起名叫"綠蛙"
Called the "Green frog".
從此我自稱伯勒先生
Started calling myself, Burroughs.
但我又開始酗酒了
But my drinking picked up.
妻子不喜歡我的那幫狐朋酒友
My wife did not care for the company of my river friends.
她決定重投前夫的懷抱
She decided to go back to her fist husband,
一個五金店的店員
a clerk in a hardware store.
臨走前  她和我說  "再見  魯本"
That was when she said, "Goodbye Reuben."
"你不夠得體"
"A love for decency does not abide in you."
一個離婚女人竟和你談體面
There is a divorced woman talking about decency.
我告訴她   "再見  諾拉"
I told her, "goodbye Nola."
"但願那賣釘子的混蛋這次能令你快樂"
"I hope that little nail-selling bastard will make you happy this time."
她把我的兒子也帶走了
She took my boy with her too.
反正他也不喜歡我
He never cared for me anyway.
估計是對他太兇了
I guess I did speak awful rough to him.
雖然我不是故意的
I did not mean anything by it.
誰都不想有比我兒子賀拉斯還笨的小孩吧
You would not want to see a clumsier child than Horace.
他至少打破了四十個杯子
I bet he broke forty cups...
那是切尼嗎
Is it Chaney?
單從腳底  可認不出
I would not recognize the soles of his feet.
那你爬上去看看
Well, you'll have to clamber up and look.
我太老太胖了
I'm too old and too fat.
現在綠蛙那多了張桌球檯
Now the Green Frog had one billiard table.
男女都能玩  不過一般都是男的在玩
Served ladies and men both, mostly men.
我曾經想自己經營
I tried to run it myself a while,
但是總是照料不好
but I couldn』t keep good help.
我一直沒有學會如何買肉
And I never did learn how to buy meat.
是他嗎
Is that him?
我覺得不是
I believe not.
把他放下來
Well, cut him down.
為什麼
Why?
我可能認識
I might know him.
所以我就跑去了德州那火烤之地
That was when I went out to the staked plain of Texas,
和弗農·沙夫特  還有個叫奧利的
and shot buffalo with Vernon Shaftoe
平頭族印第安人一起獵水牛
and a Flathead Indian named Olly.
摩門一家
The Mormons...
把沙夫特趕出了鹽湖城
had run Shaftoe out of Great Salt Lake City,
別問我為什麼
but don't ask me what it was for.
就當做誤會好了
Call it a misunderstanding and let it go at that.
那些無賴
Well,  the big shaggies,
都散了
about all gone now.
真他媽的遺憾
Damned shame.
現在能買到醃牛舌的話  三美金我也願意
Give three dollars right now for a pickled buffalo tongue.
為什麼要把他吊這麼高
Why did they hang him so high?
不知道
I don't know.
可能認為這樣可以讓他死得更慘
Possibly in the belief it would make him more dead.
我不認識這人
I do not know this man.
你吊死的嗎
You hanged him?
為什麼他把這吊死的人帶走
Why is he taking the hanged man?
他認識的人嗎
Did he know him?
不認識
He did not.
好歹是具屍體
But it is a dead body.
可以賣點錢
Must be worth something in the trade.
再說說我第二任妻子  埃德娜
Now my second wife, Edna.
她一直希望我成為律師
She had taken a notion she wanted me to be a lawyer.
買了本很厚的《丹尼爾協商技巧》
Bought this heavy book called Daniel's on Negotiable Instruments.
讓我讀
Set to make me reading it.
我從來沒看懂過
Never could get a grip on it.
我很開心能夠撇開它  離開德州
I was happy enough to set it aside and leave Texas.
我們離加拿大不遠了
There ain』t six trees between here and Canada,
這段距離幾乎寸草不生
nothing else grows but has stickers on it.
問他們...
Ask them...
-我就知道  -知道什麼
- I knew it. - Knew what?
有人跟蹤我們
We're being followed.
我剛囑咐那印第安人若發現有人跟著我們
I asked that Indian to signal with a shot
就鳴槍做信號
if someone was on our trail.
我們應該擔心嗎  警官
Should we be concerned, Marshal?
不用  勒波義夫故意打草驚蛇
No, Mr. LeBoeuf is giving us his bird dog.
一旦計謀成功  他就會飛奔而至
He wants to cut it in, once it flushed his prey.
或許我們可以來回行走
Perhaps we could double back over our tracks,
來混淆他們的追蹤
and confuse the trail in a clever way.
不用  我們就在這兒等
No, we will wait right here.
跟我們的朋友問聲好
Offer our friend a warm hello.
問問他要去哪兒
Ask him where he's going.
你不是勒波義夫
You are not LeBoeuf.
我叫福斯特
My name is Forster.
我是這堛漱醫
I practice dentistry in the nation.
也是獸醫
Also, veterinary arts.
也開刀
And medicine,
不過是在那些不會亂動的人們身上
on those humans that will sit still for it.
看來你今天有收穫啊
You have your work cut out for you there.
和一個誠懇的印第安人交易的
Traded for him with an Indian, who said he came by him honestly.
我以兩面牙醫鏡一瓶祛痰劑作為交換
I gave up two dental mirrors and a bottle of expectorant.
你們有需要
Do either of you need
醫療救助嗎
Medical attention?
沒有  要開始變冷了
No. Hey! Fixing to get cold.
你知道哪兒可以避寒嗎
Do you know of anywhere to take shelter?
我有熊皮保暖
I have my bearskin.
你可能想去小流氓博本那兒
You might want to head over to the Original Greaser Bob's.
他在卡堶菄e那鑿了個洞
He notched a dugout into a hollow along the Carrillon River.
你穿過河
If you ride the river,
就能看到了
you won't fail to see it.
小流氓博本創意旅館
Greaser Bob's, the original.
小流氓博本
Greaser Bob...
在糾察線北邊打獵
...is hunting north of the picket wire.
不會在意你借用一下的
And would not begrudge its use.
-多謝  -我已經拔了他的牙齒
- Much obliged. - Now, I have taken his teeth.
我會付價錢
I will entertain an offer,
買下他的其他部分
for the rest of him.
拿著我的大衣
Take my jacket.
輕輕地走到屋頂上
Creep onto the roof.
若他們不友好  聽我指令  弄滅煙囪
If they're unfriendly I'll give you a sign to damp the chimney.
誰在外面
Who is out there?
我們想避下寒
We're looking for shelter.
沒地方了  快滾
No room for you here! Ride on!
堶掖ㄕ魚
Who all is in there?
滾
Ride on!
我是聯邦官員
I'm a Federal officer.
堶惘魚皉b
Who's in there?
一個聖公會教徒和一個廢物
A Methodist and a son of a bitch.
我是大公雞考伯恩
This is Rooster Cogburn.
還有哥倫布·波特和五名法警
Columbus Potter and five other Marshals is out here with me.
我們有一桶煤油
We have got a bucket of coal oil.
再過一分鐘  就點燃你們的房子
In one minute we will burn your house from both ends.
你們一共就兩個人
There's only two of you.
有種你就試試看
Go ahead and bet your life on it.
你們有幾個人
How many of you is in there?
就我們倆
Just the two of us.
但是我的搭檔中槍了
But my partner's hit.
他走不動了
And he can't walk.
你是埃米特·昆西嗎
Is that Emmet Quincy?
你說房頂上的是個男的
You said it was a man on the roof.
我以為是波特呢
I thought it was Potter.
昆西  你還是一如既往的笨啊
You was always dumb, Quincy, and remain true to form.
怎麼這麼多玉米糊糊啊
This here's an awful lot of sofky.
你們在等同夥嗎
You boys looking for company?
沒有  那是我們的晚飯和早飯
No, that was supper and breakfast both.
我想早上多吃點
I like a big breakfast.
玉米糊熟了之後會變大的
Sofky always cooks up bigger than you think.
還有威士忌呢
And a good store of whiskey here as well.
你們準備這麼多吃的幹什麼
What are you boys up to, outside of cooking banquets?
我們正在吃飯
We were just having our supper.
這種鬼天氣  我們也不知道是誰在外面
We don't know who was outside in weather like this.
還以為是個瘋子呢
Might have been some crazy man.
誰都可以自稱是法警
Anyone could say he is a marshal.
我的腿好痛
My leg hurts.
當然痛了
I'll bet it does.
你上次見到奈德·彼伯是什麼時候
When was the last time you see your old pard, Ned Pepper?
不知道  他是誰啊
I do not know that. Who is he?
你居然不記得他了
I'm surprised you don't remember him.
他是個皮包骨  又警覺又敏捷
Skinny fellow, nervous and quick,
他的嘴唇都爛了
his lip's all messed up.
還是想不起來是誰
That don't bring anybody to mind.
現在有個新來的
There's a new boy
可能在奈德手下做事
that might be running with Ned.
他臉上有個又黑又亮的彈痕
He got a powder mark on his face, black polish.
他稱呼自己為切尼
Calls himself Chaney
有時也叫切爾姆斯福特
or Chelmsford sometimes.
拿一把亨利步槍
Carries a Henry rifle.
還是記不起來
That don't bring anybody to mind.
如果臉上有彈痕我應該能記住的
Black mark, I would remember that.
你什麼都不記得了是嗎  昆西
You don't remember nothing I want to know, do you Quincy?
你知道什麼  小月
What do you know, Moon?
我們不認識你要找的那幫人
We don't know those boys you're looking for.
我不認識那幫人
I don't know those boys.
我知道一定告訴你  我堅信法理
I always try to help out the law.
等我們到史密斯堡的時候
By the time we get to Fort Smith,
你這條腿就會腫得像我的帽子一樣粗了
that leg will be swelled up as tight as Dick's hat band.
這條腿就廢了
It'll be mortified.
到時候不截肢都不行了
And they'll have to cut it off.
如果你活下來了
Then if you live, I'll make
我會讓你在底特律的聯邦監獄
it two or three years in the federal house
-蹲個兩三年  -你在威脅我
- up in Detroit, there. - You're trying to get at me.
他們會教你讀書寫字的  但是
They'll teach you how to read an write up there. But...
除此之外  就有你好受的了
The rest won't be so good.
那幫傢伙連瘸子都會不放過的
Them boys, they can be hard on a gimp.
你在威脅我
You are trying to get at me.
現在
Now.
如果你能透露點關於奈德的消息
You give me some good information on Ned.
我明天就把你送回巴格比的商店
I'll take you down to Bagby's store tomorrow,
把你腿堛漱l彈取出來
get that ball taken out of your leg.
然後我會給你們三天時間離開這
Then I'll give you three days to clear the Territory.
我們真的不認識你要找的那幫人
We don't know those boys you're looking for.
反正不是他的腿
It ain't his leg.
-我...  -你能閉嘴嗎  小月
- I was... -Won't you flap your mouth, Moon?
我來說就可以了
It's best you let me do the talking.
-我要說  -我們是謹慎的捕獵者
- I would say I... - We are weary trappers.
你怎麼會跟這個老惡棍在一起
Who worked you over with the ugly stick?
臉上有彈痕的那個切尼殺了我父親
The man Chaney with the marked face, killed my father.
他也像你一樣是個醉鬼
He's a whiskey drinker like you
他因為喝醉殺了我父親
and it led to killing in the end.
好好回答法警的問題  他會幫你的
If you answer the Marshal's questions, he will help you.
我家有個很好的律師  他也會幫你的
I have a good lawyer at home, and I know he will help you too.
我有點搞不懂
I'm puzzled by these.
她為什麼會在這
Why is she here?
喬  別聽那個小兔崽子的鬼話
Joe, these people. Don't you go jawing with that runt.
我不喜歡你
I don't like you.
我希望你進監獄  我的律師才不會幫你
I hope you go to jail. My lawyer will not help you.
我腿疼的要昏過去了
My leg is giving me fits.
像你這樣的年輕人不會想失去一條腿的
A young fellow like you don't want to loose his leg.
冷靜點
Easy now.
他在引誘你
He's trying to get at you.
我從不食言
With the truth.
前天我們看到奈德和海斯了
We seen Ned and Hayes two days ago.
你腦子壞了嗎  你再說我就殺了你
Don't you act the fool, if you blow I will kill you.
我受夠了  我需要個醫生
I'm played out, I need a doctor.
我們前天碰到奈德和Hays了
We met Ned and Hayes two days ago.
該死的
God damn it.
天啊
Oh lord.
我要死了
I'm dying.
快想想辦法
Do something.
救救我
Help me.
我也無計可施了  孩子
I can do nothing for you, son.
你的夥伴要殺你  我已經替你報仇了
You pard has killed you, and I've done for him.
別讓我死在這
Don't leave me lying here.
別讓狼把我吃掉的
Don't let the wolves rip me up.
我會把你安葬的
I'll see you're buried right.
跟我說說奈德  你在哪兒看到他了
You tell me about Ned, where'd you see him?
前天
Two days ago.
在巴格比的商店
Bagby's store.
他們今晚要來這奡城豕簾釣ル犰抻k
They are coming here tonight to get remounts, and sofky.
他們剛在御夫座鐵路交叉處搶了飛之凱蒂
They just robbed the Katy Flyer at Wagoner's Switch.
飛之凱蒂: 最早擁有名字的火車
途徑密蘇里州  堪薩斯州  德克薩斯州
我要死了
I'm gone.
給我的兄弟喬治·加勒特捎個信
Send the news to my brother, George Garrett.
他在德州南部做衛理公會巡迴牧師
He is a Methodist circuit rider in South Texas.
我要不要告訴他你是個逃犯
Shall I tell him you was outlawed up.
無所謂了
It don't matter.
他知道的
He knows I'm on the scout.
我會在榮耀之路上和他相見的
I will meet him later, walking the streets of Glory.
別碰見昆西
Well don't be looking for Quincy.
他們來了之後我們怎麼幹
What do we do when they get here?
等他們自己送上門
Well, they will ride up.
到時候我們來一個甕中捉鱉
What we want is to get them all in the dugout.
我會幹掉最後一個進去的人
I'll kill the last one that goes in,
之後他們就成甕中之鱉了
then we will have them in a barrel.
你在他們身後放冷槍嗎
You will shoot them in the back?
這樣才能給他們個下馬威
It will give them to know our intention is serious.
然後我會喊話
Then I will call down
看看我們能不能活捉他們
see if they'll be taken alive.
如果抓不到活的
If they won't.
他們一出來我就開槍
I'll shoot them as they come out.
幹掉他們中的三個
I'm hopeful that three of their party being dead
估計他們也就沒膽了
will take the starch out of them.
你看上去很沉著
You display great poise.
這跟打火雞沒什麼兩樣
Aw,it is just a turkey shoot.
有一次在新墨西哥州
There was one time, in New Mexico,
我們被七個人追
we was being pursued by seven men.
我把馬調了個頭 然後用牙咬住韁繩
I turned Bo around and taken them reins in my teeth,
朝著他們直衝過去
and rode right at them boys.
拿我馬鞍堛漕漰漅軍六號朝他們開火
Firing them two navy sixes I carry in my saddle.
希望他們真是如我所想的那樣
Well.. I guess they was all married men who
都有老婆了  非常顧家  不能丟失性命
loved their families as they scattered and run for home.
這真的難以置信
Well that is hard to believe.
-什麼難以置信  -你居然一挑七啊
- What is? - One man riding at seven.
這是真的
Well, it's true.
當你足夠快足夠勇猛的時候
You go for a man hard enough and fast enough,
你的對手是不會想己方有多少人的
You don't have time to think about
他只會考慮他自己
how many is with him, he thinks about himself.
考慮如何阻擋即將到來的狂風暴雨
How he may get clear of the wrath that's about to set down on you.
他們為什麼要追你呢
Why were they pursuing you?
我搶劫了一個放高利貸的銀行
I robbed a high-interest bank.
我總不能去搶小偷吧
Can't rob a thief, can you?
我從不搶平民的錢
Never robbed a citizen.
連一塊表都沒搶過
Never took a man's watch.
搶誰都不對
It is all stealing.
那幫新墨西哥州的人也這麼想
That's the position they took in New Mexico.
就一個人
One man.
沒想到他們會派人過來探風
I didn't figure them to send a scout.
該死的
Damn.
他是勒波義夫
It is LeBoeuf.
警官  我們必須得去提醒他
Oh, we have to warn him, Marshal.
來不及了
Too late.
我們該怎麼辦啊  警官
What do we do, Marshal?
靜觀其變  他在幹什麼
We sit. What does he do?
那個穿羊皮衣服的小子就是狗屎運奈德
Him in the woolly chaps, is Lucky Ned.
就是現在
Well, that's that.
計劃失敗
Well that didn't pan out.
你把我的計劃全毀了  夥計
You managed to put a kink in my rope, partner.
我傷的很嚴重
Ah, I'm severely injured.
傷的不輕呢
Yes, you got rocks on.
我中槍了
I was also shot.
而且是被來復槍打中
By a rifle.
很有可能
Well that's quite possible.
我沒能夠按照原計劃行動
The scheme did not developed as I had planned.
你肩膀中槍了  好在子彈穿過去了
You've been shot in the shoulder, but the bullet passed through.
你嘴怎麼了
What happened to your mouth?
我可能咬著自己了
I believe I bit myself.
掉了幾顆牙  果真啊
Couple of teeth loose, and ah yeah.
舌頭都快被咬斷了
Tongue bit almost through.
你想我把它留在堶掄椄O猛的拔出來
You want to see if it'll knit or should I just yank it free.
我認識一個趕馬的人
I know a teamster.
他從馬背上摔下來的時候把舌頭咬斷了
Bit his tongue off as he was thrown from a horse.
過了很長時間才能說話
After a time he learned to make himself more or less understood.
我還是把它弄出來吧
I'll just yank it free.
現在怎麼樣了
What's that now.
What's that now?
會自己癒合的
Knit. It will knit.
好極了
Ah, very well.
舌頭上的傷口可包紮不了
It's impossible to bind a tongue wound.
真不巧  我們剛才還碰到個醫生呢
Too bad, we just ran across a doctor.
-警官  -但是我們不知道他往哪走了
- Marshal? - Of sorts, but we did not know where he was headed.
我也看到他了  所以我才過來的
I saw him too, that's how I came to be here.
這些人堥S有切尼
Neither of these men are Chaney.
我知道  這幾個人我都認識
I know it, I know them both.
那個長的很醜的是寇可·海斯
That ugly one is Coke Hayes.
這個更醜的是克萊門特·帕馬利
Him uglier stiff is Clement Parmalee.
帕馬利和他的兄弟們
Parmalee and his brothers
在旋梯山有一個老窩
have a silver claim in the Winding Stair Mountains.
狗屎運奈德的同夥肯定在那等他們
And I'll bet that's where Lucky Ned's gang is waiting.
我們今晚在這過夜  明早再去找他們
Well, we'll sleep here, follow in the morning.
但我們答應過他要把他安葬好的
But we promised to bury the poor soul inside.
地太硬了
Ground is too hard.
他要是想安葬的比較風光的話
That man wanted a decent burial,
他應該等到夏天再死
he should have gotten himself killed in summer.
晚安  小黑
Sleep well, Little Blackie.
我的直覺告訴我  明天就能找到他了
I have a notion that tomorrow we will reach our object.
我們緊隨其後
We're hot on the trail.
我們會在旋梯山追上湯姆·切尼的
Seems that we'll overtake Tom Chaney in the Winding Stairs Mountains.
他到時候肯定不會好受
I would not want to be in his shoes.
據我瞭解  切尼和
As I understand it, Chaney or
切爾姆斯福特的名字是他在德州常用的
Chelmsford, as he called himself in Texas.
殺了州議員的狗
Shot the senator's dog.
當州議員要告他的時候
When the Senator remonstrated
切爾姆斯福特把他也給殺了
Chelmsford shot him as well.
你現在也許會說
Now you could argue that the shooting
槍殺那條狗是禁止的
of the dog was clearly an instance of malum prohibitum.
但槍殺議員
But the shooting of the senator
無疑是個違法的案例
is indubitably a instance of malum in se.
違什麼
Malum in what?
違法的
Malum in se.
兩者的區別一個是事情本身的錯誤
The distinction is between an act that is wrong within itself.
另外一個是違反法律規定和道德約束的
And an act that is wrong according to our laws and mores.
是拉丁語
It is Latin.
我實在吃驚
I'm struck,
你不但挨了槍子  還被人蹂躪成這個樣
that LeBoeuf had been shot, trampled
舌頭差點都斷了
and nearly severed his tongue.
這都堵不住你的嘴
Not only does he not cease to talk,
你說話說的還挺溜
but he spills the banks of English.
有一次我離切爾姆斯福特只有兩百多米
I was within three hundred yards of Chelmsford once.
可能是最近的一次了
The closest I have been.
並且在我的夏普斯卡賓槍的射程內
With a Sharps carbine that is within range.
我在馬上  可以立馬開槍
But I was mounted, and had the choice of firing off-hand.
也可以下馬站立開槍
or dismounting and shoot from the rest.
不過這樣他就和我拉開距離了
which would allow Chelmsford to augment the distance.
我還是在馬上開槍了
I fired mounted.
但是打偏了
And fired wide.
如果你讓槍每天都睡大覺
You could not hit a man at three hundred yards
怎麼可能射中一個兩百多米遠的人
if your gun was resting on your Gibraltar.
夏普斯卡賓槍擁有強大的威力和精準度
A Sharps carbine is an instrument of uncanny power and precision.
我可沒說槍不行
I've no doubt that the gun is sound.
我衣衫襤褸  口無遮攔
My clothes are all ragged and my language is rough.
就連我的麵包也從來不服軟
My bread is corn dodgers, both solid and tough
我的生活快樂又美好
And yet I'm happy, and live at my ease
就像高粱糖漿  培根和奶酪
On sorghum molasses, and bacon, and cheese
《格媞蛾丑n  班特勒作曲
Greer county, Bantler.
我不相信他昨晚睡覺了
I do not believe he slept.
史密斯堡不遠了  勒波義夫
Fort Smith is a healthy distance, LeBoeuf.
但是我想讓你的馬往切斯特城的方向走
But I would encourage the creature you ride to head Chester.
一隻手的傢伙只會拖我們後腿
Out here a one-armed man look like an easy prey.
一隻眼睛槍法不准的傢伙
And a one-eyed man who can't shoot.
你怎麼不回去呢  考伯恩
Why don't you turn back, Cogburn?
我可得去
I'll do fine.
我知道帕馬利的老窩在哪  我又沒受傷
I know where the Parmalee's claim is. I'm uninjured,
我糧食充足  再說我們分道揚鑣了的
well provisioned and we agree to separate.
你取消合約良心會不安的
In conscience you cannot shite our agreement.
而且是你開槍打傷了我
You're the one that shot me.
勒波義夫先生說得有道理  警官
Mr. LeBoeuf has a point, Marshal.
在競賽中
It is unfair leg-up in any
朝對手開槍可有失公平
competition to shoot your opposite number.
他媽的  我不能接受
God damn it. I do not
你說是我開槍打了勒波義夫
accept it as a given that I did shoot LeBoeuf.
當時那麼多槍都響了
There were plenty of guns going off.
我聽到來福槍響了  而且感覺到了子彈
I heard the rifle, and I felt the ball.
你打偏了  考伯恩
You missed your shot, Cogburn.
我會打偏嗎
Missed my shot!
你缺只眼睛可比我缺之手差多了
You are more handicapped without the eye, then I without the arm.
我能射中六十米外的蚊子眼睛
I can hit a gnat's eye at ninety yards.
那個中國佬又賣了我一堆水貨子彈
That chinaman is running them cheap shells on me again.
我以為你要說  太陽刺進了你的雙眼呢
I thought you were going to say, the sun was in your eyes.
對了  你只有一隻眼睛
That is to say, "Your eye".
一次中兩個
Two at one time.
我扔高一點
I will chuck one high.
你別開槍
Hold fire.
-中了  -中了
- There. - There?
-是我打中的  -是你嗎
- My bullet. - Your bullet?
你要是能打中還會誤傷我的肩膀嗎
If you hit what you aim at, explain my shoulder.
先生們  在大草原上比賽射麵包
Gentlemen, shooting corn bread out here on
不能幫我們找到彼伯那幫人
the prairie is getting us no closer to the Pepper gang.
再來一次  等著瞧
One more. This will prove it.
請你別開槍
Please hold fire.
這樣就能找到回去的路
Find our way back.
狗屎運奈德
Lucky Ned?
Lucky Ned!
真不賴啊  考伯恩
Very good, Cogburn.
現在怎麼辦
Now what?
該死的
Oh, god damn it.
考伯恩才不想我吃他的糧食
Cogburn does not want me to eat out of his store.
別犯傻了
That is silly.
你一整天都沒吃了  而且這些是我的
You have not eaten the whole day,and it is my store not his.
餓死他好了
Let him starve.
他既沒追蹤
He did not track.
也沒開過槍
He did not shoot.
還好意思吃東西
Accepting food stuffs.
這都是你自找的
That was your initiative.
他一點力都沒出
He did not contribute.
他是個只會挨槍子的人
He's a man, who walks in front of bullets.
我們躲在掩護後面安全地開槍的時候
Mr. LeBoeuf drew single-handed upon the Lucky Ned Pepper gang
勒波義夫在和狗屎運奈德他們單打獨鬥
while we fired safely from cover.
-我們  -你不應該這麼說他
- We? - It is unfair to indict a man,
尤其當他的下巴都腫了
when his jaw is swollen, and tongue
舌頭都快斷了  他根本沒法辯護
mangled and is therefore unable to rise to his defense.
我可以為我自己辯護的
I can speak for myself.
只不過對於像你這種低級醉鬼
I'm hardly obliged to answer
我才懶得和你吵架呢
the ravings of a drunkard who is beneath me.
我會到其他的地方另起爐灶的
I shall make my own camp elsewhere.
你才什麼都沒干呢  考伯恩
It is you who have nothing to offer, Cogburn.
你好意思嗎
A sad picture indeed.
這不再是追蹤犯人了
This is no longer a man hunt.
是自我墮落
It is a debauch.
德州騎警隊員
The Texas Ranger
將獨自去完成任務
presses on, alone.
把這個小姑娘帶走
Take the girl.
我不幹了
I bow out.
早知現在  何必當初
A fine thing to decide once you
在這荒蕪之地撒下她不管嗎
brought her in the middle of the Choctaw Nation.
我不幹了  我金盆洗手了
I bow out, I wash my hands.
先生們  我們不能在這個時候鬧翻啊
Gentlemen we cannot fall out in this fashion.
我們馬上就要抓到湯姆·切尼了
Not so close to our goal, with Tom Chaney nearly in hand.
抓到個屁
In hand?
如果他現在沒被埋在
If he is not in a shallow grave
從這去史密斯堡路上的墳堆
somewhere between here and Fort Smith.
那就是他逃跑了
He is gone.
跑到天涯海角去了
Long gone.
這還要歸功於勒波義夫先生 我們打偏了
Thanks to Mr. LeBoeuf, we missed our shot.
我們已經打草驚蛇了
We have barked and the birds have flown.
跑了  跑了  跑了
Gone, gone, gone.
狗屎運奈德的大軍逃跑了
Lucky Ned's cohort gone.
你的五十美金也泡湯了
Your fifty dollars, gone.
跟我的威士忌一起泡湯了
Gone with whiskey.
這多顯而易見啊
Seized in evidence.
就算他們留下蹤跡也追不上了
The trail is cold if ever there was one.
我  我真是個糊塗的老頭
I'm....I'm a foolish old man
被人拉進這麼個徒勞無功的追捕
who'd been drawn into a wild goose chase.
居然還是被個悍婦和一個傻子拉進來的
by a harpy in trousers, and a nincompoop.
勒波義夫先生
Ah, Mr. LeBoeuf.
他愛在這兒待多久就待多久吧
He can wander the Choctaw Nation for as long as he likes.
當地的土著印第安人或許還把他當兄弟呢
Perhaps the local Indians will take him in.
他能說會道  沒準能當上酋長呢
Honor his gibbering by making him Chief.
小妹妹  你愛去哪兒就去哪兒吧
You sister, may go where you like.
我們的合同終止了
Our engagement is terminated.
我不幹了
I bow out.
我和你去
I'm going with you.
不行  這不可能
No, that is not possible.
我拖了你的後腿嗎
Have I held you back?
我有把我會用的柯爾特龍騎兵左輪手槍
I have a Colt's Dragoon revolver, which I know how to use.
我不會給你帶來負擔
And I will be no more of a burden to you, as I was to the Marshal.
我擔心的不是這個
That's not my worry.
你很勇敢
You've earned your spurs.
你已經證明了
That is clear now.
你已經成為一名追蹤高手了
You've been an regular old hand on the trail.
但是考伯恩說的對
But Cogburn's right.
雖然我剛才沒當著他的面承認
Even if I will not give him the satisfaction of consenting it.
確實追不上了
The trail is cold.
而且我也傷得不輕
And I am, considerably diminished.
你追蹤切尼那麼久了
How can you give up now,
怎麼能說放棄就放棄呢
after the many months you've dedicated to finding Chaney?
你展示出了極大的決心
You have shown great determination.
我之前小看你了
I misjudged you.
我挑錯人了
I picked the wrong man.
如果我們還有辦法的話  我願意幫你
I would go on with your company, if there were a clear way to go.
但我們只能在黑暗中摸索
But we'd be striking out blindly.
切爾姆斯福特已經逃跑了
Chelmsford's gone.
我們都追到這天荒地末了
We chased him right off the map.
這事就這樣
There is nothing for it.
我回德州了
I'm bound for Texas.
你也該回家了
It's time for you to go home, too.
等警官清醒之後
The Marshal, when he sobers,
你就該回去了
is your way back.
我不回去  沒找到切尼就不回去
I will not go back. Not without Chaney,
生要見人  死要見屍
dead or alive.
我也看錯你了
I misjudged you as well.
來握個手吧
I extend my hand.
勒波義夫先生  求你了
Mr. LeBoeuf! Please!
再會
Adios.
我認識你
I know you.
你叫麥蒂
Your name is Mattie.
你是小麥蒂  那個記賬員
You're little Mattie, the bookkeeper.
真巧啊
Isn't that something.
是的  而且我認識你  湯姆·切尼
Yes, and I know you, Tom Chaney.
你在這幹什麼
What are you doing out here?
來打點水
Come to fetch some water.
那你在這山媟F什麼
Oh, then what are you doing in these mountains, here?
雖然還沒被正式任命
Well I have not been formally deputized,
但我是受命於魯本·考伯恩警官
but I am acting as an agent for Marshal Reuben Cogburn
和帕克法官
and Judge Parker's court.
我要把你帶回史密斯堡
I have come to take you back to Fort Smith.
我不去
Well I will not go.
你覺得怎麼樣
How do you like that?
那邊有一治安團的警官會抓你去的
There is a posse of officers up there who will force you to go.
有意思
That is interesting news.
那邊有多少人
And how many is up there?
五十個左右
Right around fifty.
他們都武器精良  志在必得
They're all well armed and they mean business.
現在我要你渡過小溪
What I want you to do now is come on across the creek
從我面前走到那座山上去
and walk in front of me up that hill.
我還是讓那些警官來抓我吧
I think I will oblige the officers to come after me.
如果你不照著做  我就得開槍了
Well if you refuse to go, then I'll have to shoot you.
噢
Oh.
那你最好給槍上膛
Well you had better cock your piece.
一直向後扳
All the way back.
-直到鎖住  -我知道怎麼做
- Til it locks. - I know how to do it.
你不打算跟我走?
You will not go with me?
不  恰恰相反
Naw, it's just the other way around.
你得跟我走
You're going with me.
我要...
I will...AAAH!
我沒想到你會開槍
I did not think you would do it.
-現在呢  -我有根肋骨斷了
- What do you think now? - One of my short ribs is broken.
我爸爸想幫助你  你卻殺了他
You killed my father when he was trying to help you.
我有一個你從他那偷的金幣
I have one of the gold pieces you stole from him.
現在把另一個也給我
Now give me the other.
-我幹什麼都不順  -麥蒂
- Nothing has gone right for me. - MATTIE!
我在這下面
I'm down here.
現在居然被個孩子打中了
Now I'm shot by a child.
我抓住切尼了
Chaney is taken into custody!
快救我
Help me.
麥蒂
Mattie!
警官
Marshal.
把馬牽上  快走
Take them horses you got and move!
湯姆  到那山上去  別停下
Tom, get on up that hill! Don't you stop..
下面都是些什麼人
Who all is down there?
考伯恩和其他五十個警官
Marshal Cogburn and fifty more officers.
再敢撒謊  我打穿你的頭
Tell me another lie and I will stove your head in!
只有一個法警
Just the Marshal.
大公雞
Rooster.
考伯恩
Cogburn!
聽得見嗎
You hear me?
回答我  大公雞
You answer me, Rooster!
我要殺了這姑娘
I will kill this girl!
你知道我幹得出來
You know I will do it!
她對我來說什麼也不是
The girl is nothing to me!
只是個阿肯色州來的亡命者
She is a runaway from Arkansas!
非常好
That is all very well.
你建議我把她殺了嗎
Do you advise that I kill her?
隨你的便  奈德
Do what you think is best, Ned.
她只不過是個迷路的小孩
She's nothing to me but a lost child.
先好好想想
Think it over first.
我已經好好想過了
I have already thought it over!
這樣你會過來得更快
You get mounted double fast!
如果看到你越過那座禿山  向西北去
If I see you riding over that bald ridge to the northwest,
我就放了這姑娘
I will spare the girl.
給你五分鐘
You have five minutes!
馬上就會有一隊法警過來  奈德
There will be a party of marshals here soon, Ned!
把這姑娘和切尼交給我
Let me have the girl and Chaney
我就把他們引開六個小時
and I will mislead them for six hours!
太不夠意思了  大公雞
Too thin, Rooster!
太不夠意思
Too thin!
五分鐘已經快到了
Your five minutes is running!
別再說了
No more talk!
到那山上去
Get on up that hill.
安靜
Quiet there!
法雷爾  看看湯姆的傷口
Farrel, see to Tom's wound.
我能來點培根嗎
Can I have some of that bacon?
隨便你
You help yourself.
再來點咖啡
Have some of the coffee.
我不喝咖啡  我才十四歲
I do not drink coffee, I am fourteen.
我們可沒有酸奶  也沒有麵包
Well we do not have buttermilk, and we do not have bread.
我們補給不足
We are poorly supplied.
-她在哪兒  -你在這媟F嘛
- Where she is. - What are you doing here?
我要擰斷你的小細脖子
I will ring your scrawny neck.
別提這茬了
You let that go.
怎麼回事
What happened, huh?
我告訴你  你就會明白我佔理了
I will tell you and you will see that I'm in the right.
湯姆·切尼在史密斯堡槍殺了我爸爸
Tom Chaney there shot my father to death in Fort Smith
還搶了他兩個金幣
and robbed him of two gold pieces
偷了他的牝馬
and stole his mare.
我聽說考伯恩先生很有種
I was informed Rooster Cogburn had grit
就雇他來抓捕兇手
and I hired him out to find the murderer.
剛才我正好看到切尼在飲馬
A few minutes ago I came upon Chaney watering the horses.
他不服法  我便朝他開槍了
He would not be taken in charge and I shot him.
如果我把他打死
If I had killed him
現在就不會被抓住  可我的槍啞火了
I would not be now in this fix. My revolver misfired.
是這樣
They will do it.
啞火總是會讓你陷入窘境
It will embarrass you every time.
姑娘們都玩娃娃  可你喜歡槍  是嗎
Most girls like to play pretties, but you like guns, do ya?
我對槍一點興趣都沒有
I do not care a thing in the world about guns.
如果有的話  我就會有支好使的槍了
If I did I would have one that worked.
我中了埋伏  奈德
I was shot from ambush, Ned.
馬在打響鼻  不斷發出噪音
The horses was blowing and making noise.
是警官打中我的
It was that officer that got me.
你怎麼還能在那大言不慚
How can you sit there and tell such a big story?
那個坑有一百英尺深  我要把你扔進去
That pit is a hundred feet deep, and I will throw you in it.
讓你尖叫著腐爛
I'll leave you screaming in rot.
-現在你覺得怎麼樣  -你不會的
- Now how do you like that? - No you won't.
這個人不會讓你為所欲為的
This man will not let you have your way.
他是你老闆  你得照他說的做
He's your boss and you have to do as he tells you.
我從來都沒法為所欲為
Ain't nothing going my way.
前天晚上埋伏我們的人是大公雞嗎
Was that Rooster waylaid us night before last?
是考伯恩警官和我
It was Marshal Cogburn and myself.
你和考伯恩
You and Cogburn.
真厲害
Quite the posse.
咱們走吧  奈德
Let us move, Ned.
時機到了再走  醫生
In good time, Doctor.
昆西和那孩子怎麼樣了
What happened to Quincy and the kid?
他們都死了
They are both dead.
我當時身歷其境  太可怕了
I was in the very middle of it. It was a terrible thing to see.
拜託  我們走吧  奈德
Please, let us move, Ned.
法警已經走了
The Marshal's gone.
你需要好的律師嗎
Do you need a good lawyer?
我需要好的法官
I need a good judge.
寇可·海斯怎麼樣了
What happened to Coke Hayes,
這老傢伙被從馬上射下來了
the old fellow shot off his horse.
也死了
Dead as well.
這些暴行已經結束了
These depredations have come to an end.
你朋友大公雞活捉不了幾個人
Your friend Rooster does not collect many prisoners.
他不是我的朋友
He is not my friend.
他把我扔給了一群野蠻人
He has abandoned me to a congress of louts.
你從不掩飾你的想法嗎
You do not varnish your opinions.
我們出發嗎
Are we off?
咱們把飛之凱蒂那票賺的分了吧
Let us cut up the winnings from the Katie Flyer.
到老地方再分也來得及
They'll be time for that at the old place.
我騎那匹灰的
I will mount the grey.
你有別的任務
I have other plans for you.
我得和醫生騎一匹馬嗎
Must I double-mount with the Doctor?
-不  -不
- No! - Nope.
逃跑的話  兩人騎一匹馬太冒險了
Too chancy with two men up if it comes to a race.
湯姆  你和這姑娘待在這兒
Tom, you wait here with the girl.
到老馬家後我會派卡羅爾
When we reach Ma's house I will send Carroll back
帶新馬回來
with a fresh mount.
你天黑出發
You will be out by dark
我們在老地方見
and we'll meet you at The Old Place.
我不想這樣
I do not like that.
讓我和你一起走  奈德  離開這再說
Let me ride with you, Ned. Just out here anyway.
缺一匹馬
I was short a horse.
這媟|來大批法警的
Marshals will come swarming.
得有段時間呢  如果他們真來的話
Hours, if they come here at all.
他們會以為我們都走了
They'll think that we've all gone.
我不要一個人和湯姆·切尼在一起
I am not staying here by myself with Tom Chaney.
就這麼定了
That's the way I will have it.
他會殺了我的
He will kill me.
你聽見他說了  他已經殺了我爸爸
You heard him say it. He's killed my father,
現在你還要讓他殺了我
and now you will let him kill me.
他不會這麼幹的
He will do no such thing.
湯姆  你知道柏林路口吧
Tom, you know the crossing at Cypress Forks,
圓木禮拜堂附近那個
near the log meetinghouse?
到那兒的時候  你把這姑娘留下
When you mount it, you take the girl and leave her there.
明白了嗎  湯姆
You understand, Tom?
你敢動這小妹妹一根皮毛
Any harm comes to that child,
你就拿不到錢
you do not get paid.
哈羅德  讓我和你騎一匹吧
Harold, let me ride up with you.
哈羅德  我從我那份堨I五十塊錢給你
Harold, I will pay you fifty dollars out of my winnings!
我不重的
I am not heavy.
再學個牛叫  哈羅德
Do the calf again, Harold.
事事都跟我作對
Everything is against me.
你沒理由抱怨
You have no reason to whine.
你按強盜頭子的話做
If you act as the bandit chief instructed,
不傷害我  就能在老地方拿到報酬
and no harm comes to me, you will get your winnings at The Old Place.
狗屎運奈德扔下我一個人
Lucky Ned has left me,
他知道我只能步行的話肯定會被抓的
knowing I am sure to be caught when I leave on foot.
得考慮怎麼逃出生天了
Must think over my position and how I may improve it.
另一個加州金幣在哪兒
Where's the second California gold piece?
你把爸爸的馬怎麼樣了
What have you done with Papa's mare?
安靜
Keep still.
你是在猜測老地方在哪兒嗎
Are you thinking about the old place?
聽著  如果你放了我
Look here, if you let me go
我就寫書面證詞
I will swear to an affidavit
你上法庭的時候會有利於你
and once you are brought to justice, it may go easier on you.
告訴你  我能做得更好
I tell you I can do better than that.
我不需要書面證詞
I need no affidavit.
我只需要你閉嘴
All I need is your silence.
你爸和你一樣愛管閒事
Your father was a busybody like you.
說實話  我不後悔殺了他
In honesty, I do not regret shooting him.
他看不起湯姆·切尼
He thought Tom Chaney was small.
嘲笑我
Humor me.
你還要給我提供書面證詞
And you would give me an affidavit.
你們都和我對著干  所有人
You're all against me! Everybody....
這就是切爾姆斯福特
So that is Chelmsford.
終於離他這麼近了  有點奇怪
Strange to be so close to him at last.
勒波義夫先生  你怎麼會在這
Mr. LeBoeuf, how is it that you are here?
我聽到槍聲
I heard the shot,
到了河邊
and went down to the river.
考伯恩訂了個計劃
Cogburn outlined a plan.
注意腳下  那有個坑
Mind your footing, there's a pit there.
計劃堶悼L的那部分
His part,
我覺得有點魯莽
I fear is rash.
他回來抓捕狗屎運奈德
He returns for Lucky Ned.
大公雞
Yo, Rooster!
你會讓我們過去嗎
Will you give us the road?
一對四  太莽撞了
One against four. It is ill advised.
他不聽勸的
He would not be dissuaded.
奈德  有幾個人和那姑娘在一起
Hello, Ned. How many men are with the girl?
只有切尼
Just Chaney.
我們的協議已經執行了
Our agreement is in force.
上次我看見她時  她還好得很呢
She was in excellent health, when last I saw her.
法雷爾  我希望你和你兄弟都置身事外
Farrel, I want you and your brother to stand clear.
你也一樣  醫生
You as well, Doctor.
今天對你們沒興趣
I have no interest in you today.
你想幹什麼  大公雞
What is your intention, Rooster?
你以為一對四能算旗鼓相當嗎
Do you think one on four is a dogfall?
我要在一分鐘之內要你命  奈德
I mean to kill you in one minute, Ned.
或者在帕克法官有空的時候
Or see you hanged at Fort Smith
把你吊死在史密斯堡
at Judge Parker's convenience.
你選哪種
Which will you have?
你這是獨眼肥豬的
I call that, bold talk
癡心妄想
for a one-eyed fat man!
把槍拿好  你個狗娘養的
Fill your hand, you son of a bitch!
開槍啊  勒波義夫先生
Shoot them, Mr. LeBoeuf!
他們太遠了  移動太快
To far, moving to fast.
大公雞
Well, Rooster?
我被打散架了
I'm shot to pieces.
看來我們沒人
Seems neither of us,
能見到帕克法官了
get's to see Judge Parker.
主啊
Oh Lord.
這一槍真絕了
Some bully shot.
至少有四百碼
That was four hundred yards at least.
夏普斯卡賓槍  是...
the Sharps carbine, is a...
站起來  湯姆·切尼
Stand up, Tom Chaney.
勒波義夫先生
M...Mr. LeBoeuf!
你還活著嗎
Are you alive?
勒波義夫先生
Mr. LeBoeuf!
你在那兒嗎
Are you there?
我在這
I'm here.
你能爬出來嗎
Can you clamber out?
不能
I cannot.
這有蛇
There are snakes!
醒著的嗎
They awake?
醒著
Yes!
我被咬了
I am bit!
勒波義夫先生還活著嗎
Does Mr. LeBoeuf survive?
活著呢  就算撞了下頭
He does. Even a blow to the head
他也只會暈一小會
could silence him for only a few short minutes.
你哪兒被咬了
Where are you bit?
往邊上看  就現在
Look away, now.
找到她了
I have her!
把我們拉上去
Up with us!
好了  勒波義夫  扶她上馬
Worked it, LeBoeuf! Take her.
她被蛇咬了
Snakebit.
我們馬上出發
We are off.
我會盡快找人救你
I'll send help for you as soon as I can.
別亂走
Don't wander off.
我們不能扔下他
We are not leaving him!
要是我們不找醫生  你肯定活不了
I must get you to a doctor, sis, or you are not going to make it.
那槍我欠你的  夥計
I'm in your debt for that shot, pard.
永遠別懷疑德州騎警
Never doubt the Texas Ranger.
走吧
Come on.
保持健康
Ever stalwart.
我們得停下
We must stop.
小黑精疲力竭了
Little Blackie is played out.
還有好幾英里呢
We've miles yet.
快跑
Come on you.
不
No!
No.
這就對了  快跑
That's it, come on now.
不  停下
No, stop.
他逃跑了
He's getting away.
誰逃跑了  小妹妹
Who's getting away, sis?
切尼
Chaney.
不  不
No.. NO!
不  不  不
NO, no, no.
不
Oh, no.
不  住手
No, stop.
我真是老了
I've grown old.
四分之一世紀是一段漫長的時間
A quarter century is a long time.
到巴格比的店時
By the time we reached Bagby's store,
我的手已經黑了
my hand had turned black.
截肢的時候我還處於昏迷中
I was not awake when I lost the arm.
他們說考伯恩警官一直陪著我
The Marshal had stayed with me, I was told.
直到我脫離險境
'til I was out of danger.
但他在我醒來之前就離開了
But he departed before I came around.
一到家  我就給他發了邀請
Once home. I wrote him with an invitation,
請他下次經過耶爾縣的時候過來坐坐
to come by, the next time he found himself near Yell County.
並收下我欠他的五十塊錢
And collect the fifty dollars I still owed him.
我沒有收到考伯恩警官的回音
I did not hear back from Marshal Cogburn.
他也沒再出現
And he did not appear.
有一天我收到了警官的字條
Then one day I received a note from the Marshal,
還附了張傳單
with a flyer enclosed.
科爾·揚戈與弗蘭克·詹姆斯
狂野西部特別獻映  每天兩場
大公雞考伯恩  他的技巧和精力將震撼你
他說他跟著狂野西部演出團巡演
He said he was traveling with the Wild West show.
老了  也胖了
Getting older and fatter.
他們到孟菲斯時  我還是想去看看他
But I like to come visit him when the show came to Memphis,
和老朋友敘敘舊
and swap stories with an old trail mate.
狂野西部演出
就算路上拖久了  他也會理解的
He would understand if the journey were too long.
他的字條雖然簡短
Brief tho his note was.
卻錯漏百出
It was rife with misspellings.
女士您好
Yesum?
我是科爾·揚戈
I am, Cole Younger.
這是詹姆斯先生
This is Mr. James.
很遺憾告訴您  您錯過了大公雞
It grieves me to tell you that you have missed, Rooster.
他三天前去世了
He passed away three days ago.
演出團那時在阿肯色州的瓊斯伯勒
When the show was at Jonesboro Arkansas.
他葬在那兒的聯邦公墓
Buried him there at a Confederate cemetery.
魯本抱怨他晚上老睡不好
Reuben had a complaint what he referred to as night hoss?
我覺得是他承受不了暖和的天氣了
And I believe the warm weather was too much for him.
我們有過難忘的日子
We had some lively times.
你和他是什麼關係呢
What was the nature of your acquaintance?
我很久以前就認識警官了
I knew the Marshal long ago.
我們也有過  難忘的日子
We too had, lively times.
謝謝你  揚戈先生
Thank you, Mr. Younger.
繼續坐著吧  醉鬼
Keep your seat, trash.
我把他的遺體運回故地
I had the body removed to our plot
多年來常去祭拜
and I had visited it over the years.
考伯恩  耶爾縣  車站保管
毫無疑問  有很多閒話
No doubt people talked about that.
他們說  "她甚至都不認識那個人"
They say, "Well, she hardly knew the man".
"她是個神志不清的老處女吧"
"Isn't she a cranky old maid".
確實  我沒結婚
It is true, I have not married.
我沒有時間幹這種傻事
I never had time to fool with it.
魯本·考伯恩
我再也沒有德州勒波義夫警探的消息
I heard nothing more of the Texas officer, LeBoeuf.
如果他還活著  我很願意和他聯繫
If he is yet alive. I would be pleased to hear from him.
我猜他現在得有七十多歲了
I judge he would be in his seventies now.
快八十歲
And near eighty in seventy.
我希望他那亂蓬蓬的頭髮會整齊一點了
I expect some of the starch has gone out of that cowlick.
時間總是靜靜從我們身邊溜走
Time just gets away from us.
是怎樣的友誼  是怎樣的無上快樂
What a fellowship, what a joy divine,
依靠於永恆的臂彎
Leaning on the everlasting arms.
我擁有怎樣的恩惠  怎樣的平靜
What a blessedness, what a peace is mine,
依靠於永恆的臂彎
Leaning on the everlasting arms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
安全  安心  免於驚擾
safe and secure from all alarms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
依靠於永恆的臂彎
leaning on the everlasting arms.
這條朝聖之路多麼甜蜜
Oh, how sweet to walk in this pilgrim way,
依靠於永恆的臂彎
Leaning on the everlasting arms
這條路日復一日  愈發光明
Oh, how bright the path grows from day to day,
依靠於永恆的臂彎
Leaning on the everlasting arms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
安全  安心  免於驚擾
safe and secure from all alarms.
依靠  依靠
Leaning, leaning,
我依靠於永恆的臂彎
I'm leaning on the everlasting arms.